Komang! Hurry, we're gonna be late!
Komang! Ayo, nanti terlambat!
Let's take a shortcut.
Kita potong jalan saja.
The one that passes the beach? Is it faster?
Lewat pantai, Mbok? Cepat lewat sana?
Just follow me.
Sudah, ayo.
[indistinct chatter]
[dialog samar]
[kid] This garbage is from Java.
[anak laki-laki] Sampah-sampah ini dari Jawa.
But it's polluting our beach.
Tapi pantai kita yang kena.
I want to go to Java.
Aku mau ke Jawa.
I could become a musician or an artist.
Aku bisa jadi pemusik. Aku bisa jadi seniman.
Right.
Ya.
They say this garbage will drift back to Java.
Aku dengar, sampah-sampah ini akan kembali lagi ke tanah Jawa.
Maybe you can get a free ride with it.
Mungkin kau bisa menumpang sama mereka. Gratis.
Hey, garbage! Bring my little brother along!
Hei, Sampah! Ajak adikku!
Hey. I'd probably be whale dinner.
Hei. Sudah keburu mati aku, dimakan paus.
[giggles]
[terkekeh]
Like the prophet Yunus?
Seperti Nabi Yunus?
But you're the Buton version, with darker skin.
Tapi kau versi Buton. Agak gelap-gelap sedikit.
[giggling]
[tertawa]
Is that the beach?
Mbok. Itu pantainya sudah kelihatan, ya?
Sure is.
Ya.
[whines] Gosh, Arya.
[berseru] Arya.
Such a handsome young man.
Keren sekali Arya, Bu, ganteng juga.
Good morning. Om swastiastu.
Pagi, Bu. Om Swastiastu.
-Swastiastu.
- Om Swastiastu.
Going somewhere, Arya?
Mau ke mana, Arya?
I'm just heading out with Komang.
Mau keluar dulu sama Komang.
Komang!
- Komang! - Anak muda, biasa, Bu.
-Someone is going on a date. -Yes.
- Mau diajak jalan-jalan. - Ya.
Where are we going?
Mau ke mana kita?
I'll take you to a place that will make you happy.
Ada, lah. Pokoknya aku mau ajak kau ke tempat yang bikin kau bahagia.
You better mean it.
Awas kalau tidak bikin bahagia.
[ladies chatting indistinctly]
[wanita berbincang]
Mom, I'm going out for a bit.
- Komang keluar sebentar, ya. - Ya.
[comedian] I'm mad at my grandma.
[komika] Aku lagi emosi sama nenekku.
She's keeping a duck,
Karena nenekku pelihara bebek,
and she loves it more than me.
dan kasih sayangnya lebih sayang bebek ketimbang aku.
She said,
Nenek bilang,
"I take care of the duck so it's healthy and lays eggs,
"Nenek urus bebek itu supaya bebeknya sehat, supaya bertelur,
and you can have the eggs.
telurnya bisa kau ambil.
You wanna swap?
Mau terbalik?
I take care of you, but I take your eggs?"
Nenek urus kau terus, tapi telurmu Nenek ambil?"
[crowd laughing, clapping]
[audiens tertawa, tepuk tangan]
[comedian 2] The second child is so unlucky,
[komika 2] Anak kedua itu anak paling sial, ya.
always getting the first child's leftovers.
Karena kita selalu dapat harta warisan dari anak pertama. Kurang ajar itu.
I thought I had it the worst,
Aku kira aku yang paling sial,
but my fifth younger sibling is worse off.
ternyata adikku, anak kelima, lebih sial lagi.
The clothes they wear were handed down so many times,
Pakaian diwariskan lima kali ke dia.
the Adidas shirt was reduced to just the letter "A."
Baju Adidas sampai ke dia tinggal huruf "A".
[crowd laughing]
[audiens tertawa]
[comedian 2] Just wear it!
[komika 2] Pakai itu saja dulu!
[Ode] My name is Raim Laode
[Ode] Namaku Raim Laode.
I'm originally from Wangi-wangi,
Sebenarnya, aku ini dari Wangi-Wangi, Teman-Teman,
but I live in Baubau.
tapi aku tinggal di Baubau.
Am I fragrant or stinky?
Aku ini wangi atau bau?
[scattered laughter]
[audiens tertawa tipis dan Komang tertawa]
Anyone up for a sniff?
Ada yang mau tes cium?
You?
- Mau? - Tidak, Mas.
Not you, I'm talking to the lady over there.
Bukan kau, minggir dulu. Aku bicara sama Mbak yang ini.
You're way too cocky.
Kau ini percaya diri sekali.
But you can get in line, mister.
Tapi kalau kau mau, boleh antre, Mas.
-[crowd laughing] -I see you're pretty cute.
- [audiens tertawa] - Soalnya, kulihat mukamu cukup manis.
Mind sharing your skincare tips so my face can look better?
Apa perawatan wajahmu?
[crowd laughing]
[audiens tertawa]
Whoo! They're gorgeous.
Aduh! Cantik-cantik sekali.
The girls in Baubau are no match.
Dibandingkan dengan di Baubau, sudah pasti kalah.
If they start fighting…
Kalau baku pukul!
[crowd laughs]
[audiens tertawa]
…they're done for.
Sudah pasti babak belur.
[crowd cheering, clapping]
[audiens berseru, tepuk tangan]
If there is a regent election, then win…
Kalau ada pemilihan bupati, sudah pasti akan menang.
[Komang laughing]
[Komang tertawa]
[Arya] Well?
[Arya] Bagaimana?
Did I manage to make you happy?
Sukses, 'kan, aku bikin kau bahagia?
Yeah, I guess.
Ya, boleh lah.
Although that Raim guy was the only one who was funny.
Walaupun cuma satu yang lucu, si Raim itu.
That's all right.
Ya, tidak apa-apa, lah.
What matters is I get to see your smile today.
Yang penting aku bisa lihat kau senyum hari ini.
All good? I'm serious, don't play with me.
Apakah tadi bagus? Serius, jangan bercanda.
You're hilarious. You own the stage and the crowd.
Lucu. Kau kuasai panggung. Kau kuasai penonton.
He's got the hang of it.
- Dia sudah hafal benar. - Ya.
-Give it a try, just the opening? -The opening.
- Coba sebutkan satu bit aku tadi. - Bitnya yang depan.
[stuttering] First, I'll say a greeting.
[terbata-bata] Asalamualaikum dulu.
Nice!
- Nah, bagus! - Kenalkan, namaku Ode.
I can't think!
Aku lambat!
-[chuckling] -I have no business doing it.
- [terbahak-bahak] - Tidak ada urusan aku. Sudahlah.
Women like it though.
Perempuan sudah pasti suka.
-Right? -True.
- Betul? - Ya, betul.
Yet you can't get a girl. [mocking laugh]
Daripada kau, tidak ada cewek. [tertawa mengejek]
Just you wait!
Hei! Kau jangan salah!
I'm focused on chasing my dream of going to Jakarta.
Aku itu mau fokus kejar mimpiku ke Jakarta.
Once I've made it, finding a girl won't be hard.
Kalau sudah sukses, gampang cari perempuan. [berseru]
-Yeah right. -Don't worry. Tomorrow,
- Alasan saja. - Kau tenang dulu.
[Ode] Who?
Siapa?
There's someone, but we need the right timing.
Ada, tapi belum waktu yang tepat.
-You in? -[Ican] Count me in.
- Mau? - [Ican] Aku juga.
Ade.
Ade.
I want to talk to you about something.
Sebenarnya ada yang mau aku bicarakan denganmu.
What is it? About the organization?
Soal apa? Soal organisasi?
No.
Bukan.
[phone buzzing]
[getaran ponsel]
Yes, Mom?
Ya, Bu?
Okay, I'll get it for you.
Ya, nanti Komang belikan.
Okay.
Ya.
My mom wants me to buy incense. Can we drop by and get some?
Meme titip beli dupa. Nanti berhenti dulu, ya.
Okay.
Oke.
What did you want to say?
Tadi, mau bicara apa?
No, it's nothing.
Tidak. Tidak apa-apa, kok.
All right then, let's go.
Ya, ayo.
[Komang] Try some.
[Komang] Coba, Kak.
Try this sample, it's free.
Silakan dicoba. Gratis ini.
I'd like some.
Aku mau coba itu.
What is this?
Apa ini?
Mm!
[berseru pelan]
It's good.
Enak.
This is laklak.
Laklak ini.
[exclaiming] Hi!
[berseru] Hai!
He ate it first.
Dia makan duluan.
Have you paid for that? We want some too.
Kau bayar dulu. Kita mau makan juga, 'kan?
It's not free?
Ini tidak gratis?
-How could you? -Pay for it! It's their income.
- Parah sekali. - Bayar! Ini bulanan mereka.
Should I spit it out?
- Aku keluarkan lagi? - Ini gratis.
Come on, stop joking!
Kalian bercanda terus!
Are you guys close?
Jadi, kalian sudah akrab?
Ade, this is Ode.
Ade, ini Ode.
Raim Laode.
Raim Laode.
Ode, this is Ade. Komang Ade.
Ode, ini Ade. Komang Ade.
-Ade, Ode. What a match! -Sure is!
- Ade, Ode. Cocok! - Cocok!
-Like, onde mande. -Ote-ote!
- Kayak, onde mande. - Ote-ote!
[giggling]
[tertawa]
Onde mande, the Betawi art show?
Onde mande itu pertunjukan seni khas Betawi?
Exactly! [chuckling]
Ya, benar! [tertawa]
That's really cheap.
Agak jauh, itu.
Babe, it's funny, right?
Lucu, 'kan, Kekasihku?
[forced laughter]
[tertawa palsu]
It's funny, right?
Ya, 'kan?
Babe, I wanna go over there.
Sayang, ayo main itu.
-Come on, let's play. -Come on.
- Main itu. Ayo. - Mari main.
Hey, Raim.
Hei, Raim.
Good luck.
Semangat.
[bright music playing]
[musik penuh harapan]
[Ode] Since I…
Oh ya, tadi aku 'kan…
asked for your food,
sudah minta makananmu.
can I
Boleh…
also ask… for your number?
Kalau aku minta nomormu juga, boleh?
Sure.
Boleh.
Sorry. Let me hold that for you.
Maaf. Sini aku pegang. Biar tidak repot.
[deep breaths]
[menghela napas]
This is my dad's number.
Ini nomor bapakku.
Huh?
Apa?
Is this okay?
Ini tidak apa-apa?
[chuckles] It used to be his.
[terkekeh] Dulunya.
[chuckling] Oh.
[tertawa] Oh.
So now it's your number?
Tidak apa-apa kalau begitu. Yang penting sekarang sudah nomormu, 'kan?
It'd be awkward if I called and your dad picked up.
'Kan tidak lucu kalau nanti aku telepon yang angkat bapakmu.
What would I say?
Aku mau bilang apa nanti?
Should I ask for more laklak?
Masa minta laklak lagi?
It would be funny.
Memang lucu.
Since my dad has passed away, he can't pick up.
Soalnya bapakku sudah meninggal, jadi, tidak mungkin diangkat sama dia.
Are you serious?
Kau serius?
I'm sorry, I didn't know…
Aku minta maaf. Aku tidak tahu…
I'm just kidding. [chuckling]
Bercanda. [terkekeh]
So he's still alive?
Berarti bapakmu masih hidup?
He passed away. But that's my number.
Sudah meninggal. Tapi itu nomorku kok.
[chuckling] Oh.
[tertawa] Oh.
Dark jokes, huh?
Komedi gelap ini.
You've got a knack for being a comedian.
Ada bakat jadi komika.
Umm…
[bergumam]
If I ask you out sometime,
Kapan-kapan, kalau aku ajak jalan,
would you mind?
bisa?
[man] Raim!
[pria] Raim!
See you.
Permisi.
Where are you, dan?
Kau di mana?
[tender music]
[musik lembut]
Boy!
Boy!
What?
Apa?
I need your advice.
Aku butuh saran!
I'm going out with a girl.
Aku mau jalan sama cewek.
Your motorcycle is free, right?
Motor tidak dipakai, 'kan?
Yeah, it's free because it's broken.
Ya. Tidak dipakai karena dia mogok.
What about Dad's?
- Motor Bapak bagaimana? - [Boy] Dia pakai beli ampelas.
Gosh, again?
Aduh! Beli ampelas terus.
Does he want to polish the streets?
Dia mau bikin halus jalan?
Maybe.
Mungkin.
I'm busy here.
Aku lagi pusing sama ini.
If you want to ride it, go get this fixed.
Kalau kau mau bawa motor, kau perbaiki barang ini.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
Komang, are you going out with Arya?
Mang, mau keluar dengan Arya?
No.
Tidak.
It's a friend I haven't introduced you to.
Meme belum kenal, teman lain.
A guy?
Laki-laki?
Don't stay out too late.
Jangan malam-malam, ya.
I won't.
Ya.
Why are you smiling like that?
Kenapa mukamu menyeringai begitu?
Why? Do I look scary?
Kenapa? Seram?
Yeah.
Ya, seram.
You scared the life out of me.
"Seram-an" jantung aku lihatnya.
[chuckles]
[tertawa]
It's not funny, isn't it?
Tidak lucu sepertinya, ya?
It's funny.
Lucu.
You, I mean.
Maksudnya kau.
[chuckling shyly]
[tertawa tersipu]
Here.
Ini.
[Ode] Do I smell?
[Ode] Aku bau badan?
Huh?
Apa? Tidak.
Don't you worry, I've showered.
Kau tenang saja, aku sudah mandi.
No skin diseases either. All good.
Aku juga tidak ada penyakit kulit. Aman.
I wasn't thinking that.
Aku tidak berpikir begitu.
So why are you sitting so far away?
Terus, kenapa kau duduk jauh sekali?
I could even put a ship between us.
Aku bisa taruh kapal feri di tengah kalau mau.
Eyes on the road.
Lihat ke jalanan.
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
[Ode] I'm back! I'm Raim Laode.
[Ode] Kembali lagi bersama aku, Raim Laode.
I'll be your tour guide at Keraton Fort today.
Hari ini aku akan menjadi pemandu wisata kalian
[Komang chuckles]
[Komang terkekeh]
But it's strange, it's a little empty today.
Tapi tumben sekali, sepi pengunjung hari ini.
Just one guest.
Cuma satu orang.
What's your name?
Dengan Adik siapa?
Komang Ade.
Komang Ade.
-Oh, Komang Ade. -[Komang chuckles]
- Oh, Komang Ade. - [Komang terkekeh]
I see.
Ya.
This is Keraton Fort,
Jadi, ini adalah Benteng Keraton.
the largest fort in the world.
Ini benteng terbesar di dunia.
It's an Indonesian fort that was built by the locals
Salah satu benteng di Indonesia yang dibangun oleh orang-orang lokal,
of the Buton Sultanate.
yaitu orang Kesultanan Buton.
Miss Komang Ade,
Adik Komang Ade,
do you know who normally constructs forts?
tahu tidak, biasa benteng ini dibangun oleh siapa?
[hums]
[menggumam]
Komang!
Sama Komang!
No.
Tidak.
Construction workers?
Sama tukang bangunan?
Not quite.
Belum tepat.
Laode!
Sama Laode!
Perhaps.
Bisa jadi!
[Komang chuckles]
[terkekeh]
I've been wondering, what do La Ode and Wa Ode mean?
Aku penasaran dari dulu, La Ode dan Wa Ode apa artinya?
It's simple.
Sederhana saja.
"La" means men, "Wa" means women,
"La" itu laki-laki, "Wa" itu wanita,
and "Ode" means overdose.
dan "Ode", overdosis.
-I'm being serious! -[giggling]
- Jangan seperti itu. Aku serius lo. - [terkekeh]
Okay, okay.
Ya.
Ode is a title of nobility in Buton.
Jadi, Ode itu adalah gelar kebangsawanan Buton.
There's La Ode and Wa Ode.
Ada La Ode dan juga Wa Ode.
La means La ilaha illallah,
"La" itu La ilaha illallah,
and Wa means Wa asyhadu anna muhammadar rasulullah.
dan "Wa" itu Wa asyhadu anna muhammadar rasulullah.
So Buton's people carry both God's and the prophet's names.
Jadi, di antara nama orang-orang Buton itu terselip nama Rasul dan nama Tuhan.
What does Komang mean?
Kalau Komang artinya apa?
The third child.
Anak ketiga.
That's it?
Sudah? Itu saja?
Yeah, that's it. The third child.
Ya, itu saja. Anak ketiga.
No historical significance?
Tidak ada embel-embel sejarah atau apa, begitu?
I don't think so.
Tidak sepertinya.
Oh, I see.
Oh, ya.
You've been in Sulawesi for some time, right?
Kau sudah lama di Sulawesi. Bagaimana?
It must be so different from Bali, where tourists are everywhere.
Pasti beda sekali dengan Pulau Bali yang di mana-mana bule semua, 'kan?
[hums]
[menggumam]
Feels the same.
Sama saja.
As long as my mom is happy, I'm fine.
Kalau aku, yang penting ibuku bahagia.
Even so, sometimes she nags a lot.
Walaupun, tetap saja kadang suka mengomel terus.
Despite all the complaints,
Tapi walaupun suka mengomel begitu,
when something goes wrong,
ketika kita ada apa-apa,
our mom is always the first one to help.
pasti orang pertama atau garda terdepan adalah ibu kita yang tolong kita.
You're totally different on-stage than when we're talking like this.
Beda kau, ya, waktu komedi tunggal sama mengobrol biasa seperti ini?
Hmm?
Apa?
I knew it.
Aku tahu!
You agreed to hang out with me
Kenapa kau mau jalan sama aku
because of love at first sight, right?
karena kau sudah cinta sama aku pada pandangan pertama, 'kan?
[exclaiming]
[memekik]
You're so full of yourself.
Percaya diri sekali orang ini.
[chuckling]
[terkekeh]
It just dawned on me.
Aku baru sadar.
I'm out with Komang,
Aku mau jalan sama Komang,
whose name means the third child,
yang artinya anak ketiga,
known as Ade, three letters,
biasa dipanggil Ade, tiga huruf,
and I borrowed a motorcycle to go with Komang, known as Ade,
dan tadi aku pinjam motor untuk jalan sama Komang, yang biasa dipanggil Ade,
from a third friend.
ke tiga kawan.
[whispers] In the name of God.
[berbisik] Bismillah.
Do you… want to
Kau… mau tidak
go out with me?
pacaran dengan aku?
just so we're both on the same page.
supaya tujuan kita jelas, tidak ke mana-mana.
Hold on, we just met. Isn't it too soon?
Tunggu dulu. Baru saja kita bertemu, masa langsung pacaran?
Right.
Ya.
You have a point.
Benar juga.
How about this?
Kalau tidak, begini saja.
We're going to hang out for three hours.
Kita akan jalan selama tiga jam.
Let's try being in a relationship.
Kita coba dulu saja pacaran.
But if not,
Tapi kalau kau rasa tidak cocok,
you can end it.
kau boleh sudahi juga.
So?
Bagaimana?
Handshake?
Salaman dulu.
To seal the deal.
Biar resmi.
Our dating.
Pacaran.
Aw, man.
Aduh.
You don't want to shake hands with a Buton noble?
Kau tidak mau salaman sama bangsawan Buton?
[Ode chuckles]
[Ode terkekeh]
["Lesung Pipi" by Raim Laode playing]
["Lesung Pipi" oleh Raim Laode bermain]
Who do we have here?
Ya, dengan siapa di sini?
What's your name?
Dengan Adik siapa?
-Ode. -Okay, Ode.
- Ode. - Ya, Adik Ode.
Dolphins are capable of echolocation.
Jadi, kalau lumba-lumba itu punya kemampuan namanya ekolokasi.
Echolocation is…
Ekolokasi itu…
I can't focus if you film me like that.
Kalau aku disorot kamera begitu, aku tidak bisa berpikir.
[laughing]
[terbahak-bahak]
Keep going.
Tidak apa-apa. Lanjutkan.
["Lesung Pipi" by Raim Laode continues playing]
♪ Kusadar lirikku ♪
[music fades]
[lagu memudar]
Thanks for the ride home.
Terima kasih ya sudah mengantar aku pulang.
Sure. Wait.
Ya. Sebentar.
So…
Jadi, begini…
We've been dating for three hours,
Kita sudah pacaran selama tiga jam,
and I said that if you think we're a match, we'll continue,
dan aku sudah bilang sama kau, kalau kau rasa cocok, kita lanjutkan.
but if not, feel free to end it.
Dan kalau kau rasa tidak cocok, kau putuskan saja aku.
It's okay if you decide to end it.
Tapi, sebenarnya, tidak apa-apa juga kalau kau putuskan aku.
I'll just go home feeling sad.
Paling aku pulang dengan keadaan bersedih.
You see the sky?
Kau lihat langit itu?
It's cloudy, as if it's feeling sad.
Sudah mendung. Seperti akan bersedih juga.
Ready to cry.
Mau menangis.
So? Do we continue dating?
Jadi, bagaimana? Kita lanjutkan?
It's raining!
Hujan!
Huh?
Eh?
[Komang laughs]
[Komang tertawa]
Why is it raining so hard all of a sudden?
Kok bisa tiba-tiba hujan deras begini?
No idea.
Tidak tahu juga.
Is it okay if I stay here for a bit?
Tapi aku tidak apa-apa, 'kan, menumpang di sini?
It's okay.
Tidak apa-apa.
Hey.
Hei.
Do you mind if I pray here?
Aku boleh menumpang salat sebentar, tidak?
Maghrib is almost over.
Sudah mau lewat magrib.
Yeah, sure.
Ya, boleh.
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
Come in.
Masuk saja.
You can pray here.
Kalau mau salat, bisa di sini.
Okay.
Ya.
[groans] It's dead.
[mengeluh] Mati.
Can I borrow your phone real quick?
Aku boleh pinjam ponselmu sebentar, tidak?
-This way. -Oh.
- Oh, ini. - Oh.
Is your Qibla facing west?
Kiblatmu ke barat, ya?
It's the opposite of mine.
Berlawanan sama arah sembahyangku.
I see.
Oh, ya.
The bathroom is over there.
Kalau mau pakai kamar mandi, ada di sana.
Let me dry your jacket.
Oh, ya. Ini jaketnya dikeringkan saja.
-You don't have to. -No worries. It should dry out.
- Tidak apa-apa? - Tidak apa-apa, biar kering nanti.
[Ode praying in Arabic]
[berdoa dalam bahasa Arab]
-[thunder rumbles] -Amen.
- [guntur bergemuruh] - Amin.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
Ma'am.
Ibu.
Sorry, I was praying…
Maaf, aku menumpang salat…
Hi.
Hai.
It's still pouring.
Masih deras.
Looks like it'll last a while.
Ya. Lama sepertinya.
What do I do?
Aduh, bagaimana ini?
I can't go home in the rain.
Tidak mungkin kalau aku hujan-hujanan.
I mean, you can.
Kalau itu, mungkin.
If anything, your jacket might get a cold.
Paling jaketmu saja yang masuk angin.
Burping and all. Just give it a massage.
Beserdawa. Tinggal dikerok saja.
Give it a go and update me tomorrow.
Coba saja. Besok kabari.
Your jokes aren't bad at all.
Lumayan. Lawakanmu lumayan.
You'll be even funnier if I mentor you.
Nanti coba aku bimbing biar lebih lucu.
See you later.
Aku pamit.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Om swastiastu.
Om Swastiastu.
[movie playing indistinctly on TV in the distance]
[berdeham]
[coughing in the distance]
[suara batuk samar]
Dear?
Pak?
Dear.
Bapak.
Quit smoking. Drink some water.
Sudah, jangan merokok terus. Minum dulu.
-Gosh. -Just a minute, dear.
- Aduh. - Sebentar, Bu.
Just a minute.
Sebentar.
-That's enough. -Where's the movie?
- Itu sudah banyak. - Mana tontonanku?
You've smoked a lot today.
Hari ini sudah banyak sekali merokoknya.
Last one.
Ini terakhir.
You keep saying that.
Dari kemarin terakhir terus.
-I swear. -Dad.
- Ini paling terakhir. - Bapak.
Buy a spark plug? The motorcycle is broken.
Beli busi, ya? Motor rusak.
-What's wrong? -It won't start.
- Kenapa juga? - Tidak bisa menyala.
-Change the spark plug. -Peace be upon you.
- Kau ganti businya. - Asalamualaikum.
[Ode's dad and Ode's mom] And upon you peace.
Wa'alaikumsalam warahmatullahi wabarakatuh.
Everyone's here.
Ada Bapak, Kakak Boy, sama Mama di sini.
[Ode's dad] Yes.
- [ayah Ode] Ya. - [terkekeh]
You were out in the rain? You might get sick.
Kau ini habis hujan-hujanan?
Don't worry, Mom. I'm happy, I won't get sick.
Tidak apa-apa, Mama. Sedang senang, tidak mungkin sakit.
He'll be fine.
Pasti aman. Tidak mungkin dia sakit.
Because he's in love.
Dia itu sedang jatuh cinta.
Don't get some kid pregnant, you hear me?
Hati-hati, nanti hamil anak orang!
-Dear! -Oh my God, Dad!
- Bapak! - Astagfirullah! Bapak kalau bicara…
Sheesh.
Hei.
Ode!
Ode!
Calm down, dear.
Sudah, Bu. Sudah.
-What woman did he brave the rain for? -He's young. Let him be.
- Wanita mana yang dia bawa hujan-hujanan? - Biarkan saja, anak muda.
He's young. Let him be.
Biarkan saja.
[grunts]
- [menggerutu] - Awas, lagi nonton ini.
Psst.
Sut. Hei, siapa?
Wanna know?
Mau tahu?
The girl he's courting
Yang dia bawa itu
is the daughter
anaknya
of a mother
mamanya.
and of a father.
Anaknya bapaknya.
She was born to her parents.
Anak orang tuanya.
The aunt's niece?
Keponakan tantenya.
Maybe.
Mungkin.
-Yeah. -[chuckles]
- Ya. - [terkekeh]
Have you prayed?
Kau sudah salat?
[wheezing]
[tergelak]
-Why are you laughing? -Funny.
- Kenapa Bapak tertawa? - Lucu.
-She's funny. -That means my joke is funny.
- Ini lucu. - Berarti lucu lawakanku.
-No! I'm the funny one! -I thought I was funny.
- Bukan! Mamak yang lucu! - Tadi lucu.
[giggling]
[terkekeh]
She's so lovely.
Lucu sekali wanita ini.
What are you looking at?
Lihat apa itu?
You're so nosy.
Kepo saja.
What's with the heart eyes?
Punya mata sudah seperti ada hatinya begitu.
You're so annoying!
Kau iseng sekali!
Stop bothering me and go pray.
Ganggu saja. Sana kau salat dulu, cepat!
Let me see.
Biar aku lihat, sini.
Don't fall for her too.
Awas, nanti kau cinta juga sama dia.
-Just a peek. -Let me kiss her.
- Jangan lama-lama lihatnya. - Aku cium dia.
Stop!
Jangan!
That's mine!
Punya aku ini!
[smooches] I kissed her first.
[kecupan] Aku cium duluan.
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
[Ode] Did you know?
[Ode] Kau tahu, tidak?
I'm the luckiest person on Earth
Aku ini manusia paling beruntung sedunia.
because I get to see your beautiful smile.
Aku bisa mendapatkan senyuman cantikmu itu.
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
Let's just go.
Sudah, ayo naik.
Ma'am, peace be upon you.
Ibu, asalamualaikum.
-Mom. I'm heading out. -Om swastiastu.
- Meme, pergi dulu, ya. - Om Swastiastu.
Come on.
Ayo.
[tender music continues playing]
[musik lembut berlanjut]
Over there.
Itu… Itu lumba-lumba, bukan?
Islam.
Islam.
That's Pevita Pearce. Take a good look!
Itu Pevita Pearce. Coba kau lihat itu!
-You're right. -But she's a Muslim, right?
Tapi Islam juga, 'kan?
Yeah, it says so on her Wikipedia.
Ya, di Wikipedia dia masih Islam.
How about this one?
Yang ini bagaimana?
Huh?
Bagaimana?
Stay out of it. They've been dating for a year.
Kau tidak usah ganggu orang. Orang ini sudah satu tahun pacaran.
Let him have his freedom.
Biarkan dia bebas.
Yeah, seriously.
Ya, bagaimana kau ini?
What freedom? Your freedom led them with no end in sight.
Bebas apa? Gara-gara bebasmu itu jadi begini. Tidak ada ujungnya.
All because you introduced them.
Gara-gara kau yang kenalkan dia.
Why blame me?
Kenapa aku yang salah?
I only opened the door. He took it further.
Aku cuma buka pintu, dia yang lanjutkan dosanya.
You still introduced them to the path of sin.
Kau bicara dosa? Sama saja, kau yang kenalkan.
Cut it out!
Sudah!
If you want to go for it, just go for it. I'll skip.
Kalau kau mau, dekati saja. Aku lewat dulu.
Stop being distracted by women. Let's focus on our careers.
Benar. Kau mengurusi perempuan terus. Kita harus fokus pada karier.
Yeah. Got any news?
Ya. Ada info apa?
I just remembered something.
Aku baru ingat. Kemarin kau cerita,
You want to do stand-up with Boy, right?
ingin komedi tunggal sama Kak Boy, 'kan?
You should go for the audition.
Mending kau audisi.
I think this is the right choice. It could take you to Jakarta.
Menurutku, ini jalan yang pas. Ini bisa menjadi sarana kau ke Jakarta.
True. There's plenty of Muslim women over there.
Benar, masuk akal. Banyak juga cewek Islam di sana.
Are girls all you think about?
Cewek terus yang keluar dari mulut orang ini.
When's the audition?
Kapan audisinya?
Um… tomorrow.
[bergumam] Besok.
-[Husni] He's talented, you know. -[Ican] Go practice.
- [Husni] Karena kau ada bakat. - [Ical] Ya, latihan saja kau.
[phone dings]
[denting ponsel]
-[Ican] Focus. -[Husni] They are funny.
- [Ican] Fokus. - [Husni] Dia memang lucu.
But our group…
Tongkrongan kita saja…
[exclaims] Gosh! Oh my God.
[berseru] Astagfirullahaladzim!
I need to stop by Ade's place first.
Sebentar, aku ke Ade dulu, ya.
To help her prepare for Galungan.
Aku mau bantu dia adakan Galungan.
Oh my God. Huh?
Astagfirullah.
-Is he converting? -He's faltering.
- Dia yang pindah. Tidak kuat pondasinya. - Goyang.
Lakum dinukum waliya din.
Lakum dinukum waliya din.
-For you is your religion… -There he goes.
- Untukmu agamamu… - Ceramah.
-…and for me is my religion. -Preach.
- …untukku agamaku.
You're a preacher now?
Pendakwah?
-It's only been a year. -Balinese girls are there.
- Baru satu tahun, langsung… - Banyak cewek-cewek Bali di sana.
I'm coming. Balinese girls, seriously?
Segera berangkat. Cewek-cewek Bali?
-[traditional Balinese music] -[indistinct chatter]
- [musik tradisional Bali] - [dialog samar]
Om swastiastu. Peace be upon you.
Om Swastiastu. Asalamualaikum.
Om swastiastu.
Om Swastiastu.
Sorry I'm late, I was looking after my kid.
Maaf Mbok Dek telat, tadi habis mengurus anak.
No worries.
Tidak apa-apa.
In Bali, we'd make a pork lawar.
Kalau di Bali, sudah pasti bikin lawar babi.
I checked the market earlier, but they didn't have it.
Aku sudah cari di pasar tadi. Tidak ada.
It's hard to find here.
Agak susah carinya di sini.
Squid lawar is good as well.
Lawar cumi juga enak, kok.
Not everyone is able to eat pork lawar.
Lagi pula, kalau kita bikin lawar babi, tidak semua orang bisa makan, 'kan?
It'll taste especially great if it's Kadek's cooking.
Apalagi kalau Mbok Kadek yang masak, enak pasti.
Thank you.
Ya, terima kasih.
It's done.
Sudah jadi, Mbok.
Arya was supposed to be your future son-in-law.
Mbok, calon menantumu itu seharusnya Arya.
He's kind, handsome, successful,
Sudah baik, sudah ganteng, mapan juga.
and he's like a brother.
Sudah seperti saudara.
Not Raim.
Bukan Raim.
They're just friends. It's nothing serious.
Mereka tidak serius, hanya berteman.
How can it be friendship when they're always together everywhere?
Mana ada berteman seperti itu?
Warn Komang to not end up like Kadek
Beri tahu Komang baik-baik, supaya tidak seperti Kadek nanti.
before it's too late.
Agar tidak terlanjur basah.
If you pass away,
Kalau kau nanti meninggal,
who's going to take care of your Ngaben ceremony?
siapa yang mengurus upacara Ngabenmu?
Auntie, where are the flowers?
Bu, bunga ada di mana, ya?
In the kitchen, on the bottom shelf.
Ada di dapur, di paling bawah.
Just have a look there.
Dicari-cari saja di sana.
-Okay. -Thanks.
- Baik. - Terima kasih.
How is it?
Bagaimana?
This lawar is as lovely as you, Komang.
Cantik sekali lawarnya, sama cantiknya dengan Komang.
Mom. I can't believe you're comparing me to squid lawar!
Meme! Masa Komang disamakan dengan lawar cumi?
I'm a dolphin, not a squid.
Komang itu lumba-lumba, bukan cumi-cumi.
There's no such thing as dolphin lawar. This girl…
Mana ada lawar lumba-lumba? Kau ini…
Komang.
Mang.
Did you hear?
Kau tahu, tidak?
Arya secured a job in Kalimantan.
Arya itu sudah keterima kerja di Kalimantan.
He's bound for success,
Calon sukses, dia itu.
and he's from Bali, just like us.
Sesama saudara Bali, dia itu.
I'm gonna go help Kadek.
Komang mau bantu Mbok Kadek dulu, ya.
Komang.
Komang.
I'm talking to you right now.
Dengar kalau Meme bicara.
Sit!
Duduk!
No mother wants her child to suffer.
Tidak ada ibu yang mau anaknya susah, Mang.
They only wish them happiness.
Semua ibu itu pasti mau anaknya bahagia.
If your own mother, who gave you life, thinks this way,
Meme yang melahirkan kau saja berpikir begitu.
imagine how your Creator feels about you.
Bagaimana dengan Tuhan yang menciptakanmu?
Gosh.
Aduh.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
Thanks.
Terima kasih.
Do I look like a Made or a Nyoman?
Bagaimana? Aku sudah mirip Made atau Nyoman?
You do.
Mirip.
You look like an "I Nyoman Hanuman."
Mirip I Nyoman Hanuman namanya.
[monkey noises]
[suara monyet]
Lovely weather today.
Bagus cuacanya hari ini, ya.
You're taking the audition to go to Jakarta?
Kau audisi ke Jakarta?
Yeah.
Ya.
Is this because of what my mom said earlier?
Ini karena kau dengar omongan Meme tadi, ya?
What did she say?
Memangnya Meme bilang apa?
I'm serious.
Aku serius.
Me too. I didn't hear anything.
Aku juga serius. Aku tidak dengar tadi.
Oh, I know.
Aku tahu.
I bet she's proud that I look like Ade.
Pasti Meme bangga sekali, lihat aku mirip Ade begini.
By the way, what is this for?
Oh, ya. Omong-omong ini buat apa?
This is an offering.
Ini untuk persembahan.
To show our gratitude.
Bentuk rasa syukur kita.
How long will you stay in Jakarta?
Berapa lama kau di Jakarta?
[sighs] I can't say for sure.
[menghela napas] Aku juga tidak tahu kalau soal itu.
If I make it big, amen.
Ya, nanti kalau aku sukses, amin.
I might stay there for good.
Aku bisa seterusnya di sana.
I hope you succeed and make it to Jakarta.
Ya, aku doakan kau bisa lolos, terus ke Jakarta.
[exclaims]
[berseru]
That's exactly what I need, prayers from all directions!
Itu dia yang aku butuhkan! Doa dari segala penjuru.
If both our Gods bless me,
Kalau Tuhanmu dan Tuhanku sudah bersatu memberi restu, habis sudah.
there's no way I'll fail.
Sudah pasti berhasil, tidak mungkin gagal.
[chuckling]
[terkekeh]
[somber music playing]
[musik sendu]
[phone dings]
[denting ponsel]
Komang.
Komang.
Your mom's asking for you. She needs your help.
Kau dipanggil Meme. Disuruh bantu dia.
Okay. I'll go over there.
Oh, ya. Ya sudah, sebentar dulu, ya.
What about me?
Tapi aku bagaimana?
Need my help?
Mau aku bantu?
No need, I don't want to trouble you.
Tidak usah. Merepotkan itu, Mas.
-All good. -Come on.
- Aman. - Ayo.
Take it easy.
Ya. Santai.
Relax.
Santai saja.
Just completely ignore my presence, huh?
Anggap saja aku tidak ada di sini.
[man] The winner is… Raim Laode!
Yang akan berangkat ke Jakarta… Ode, Raim Laode!
[cheering, clapping]
[bersorak, tepuk tangan]
Five scrubs in! If I keep at it, a genie will come out!
Aku sudah sikat lima kali. Lama-lama keluar jin kalau kita gosok!
[Ode's dad] Just be patient.
Tidak. Kau ini.
You're always so fussy when I ask for help.
Selalu cerewet kalau diminta tolong.
[Ode] Peace be upon you!
Asalamualaikum!
And upon you peace and God's mercy and blessings.
Wa'alaikumsalam warahmatullahi wabarakatuh.
[Ode's dad exclaims]
[ayah Ode berseru]
[Ode's dad] My beloved son is here.
Anak kesayangan Bapak sudah datang.
[Ode groans]
[mengerang]
What? You need anything?
Kalau begini, dia pasti ada maunya.
You finish that.
Kau lanjutkan itu.
-Here you go. -Go.
- [mengeluh] - Apa ini? Buat aku?
I brought some food for dinner.
Ini makanan buat nanti malam.
Oh. I'll take it upstairs.
Oh. Bawa ke atas, ya.
Okay.
- Ya. - Oke.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
And upon you peace and God's mercy and blessings.
Wa'alaikumsalam warahmatullahi wabarakatuh.
Hello.
Ibu.
[indistinct chattering]
[obrolan samar]
-Hey! -What, Dad?
- Hei! - Bapak, kenapa?
Why do you keep on staring at her?
Kenapa kau perhatikan dia terus?
She's not going to disappear.
Dia tidak akan hilang.
Are you serious about her?
Kau serius sama dia?
Of course.
- [berseru pelan] Serius, lah. - [mengejek]
I wouldn't bring her here if I wasn't.
Kalau tidak serius, untuk apa aku bawa ke sini?
You'll face a heavy burden.
Berat nanti beban hidupmu.
I know that, Dad.
Ya, aku tahu itu.
Hey, Raim.
Hei, Im.
Is she serious about you?
Dia serius sama kau?
I think so.
Seharusnya serius.
[skeptical huff]
[terkesiap]
I'm your son, don't treat me like that.
Bapak, aku ini anakmu. Jangan begitu kepadaku.
Listen to me.
Kau dengarkan bapakmu.
It's in human nature
Manusia itu
to love and care for one another,
ditakdirkan untuk saling menyayangi antarsesama,
regardless of religion.
apa pun agamanya.
But as a leader,
Tapi kalau kau nanti jadi imam,
your follower should be of the same faith.
kau juga harus punya makmum yang seiman.
Anyway, don't stress about it.
Sudahlah, tidak usah kau pikirkan terlalu serius.
Leave it to fate.
Percayakan saja sama takdir.
If you're meant to be with her,
Kalau nanti kau ditakdirkan untuk bersatu sama dia,
there will be a way.
pasti ada jalannya.
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
-Now that's my dad. -"Now that's my dad."
- Begitu. Ini baru Bapakku. - "Ini baru Bapakku."
Peace be upon you!
Asalamualaikum!
[Ode's mom] And upon you peace and God's mercy and blessings.
Wa'alaikumsalam warahmatullahi wabarakatuh.
[Ode] And upon you.
[Ode] Alaikum salam.
[Ode's dad] There he is!
Ini dia orang yang ditunggu-tunggu.
Mr. Dua.
Bapak Dua.
-How are you?
- Sehat? - Bagaimana?
-I'm good, thanks to God. -Thank God.
- Alhamdulillah, baik. - Alhamdulillah.
I heard you're going to Jakarta?
Katanya mau ke Jakarta?
Soon.
- Ya, nanti. - Sudah makan?
[in Arabic] I take refuge in Allah from the cursed devil.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari godaan setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan nama Allah yang Maha Pengasih dan Maha Penyayang.
O Allah, bless us in what You have provided for us,
Ya Allah, berkahilah kami pada apa yang telah Engkau karuniakan
and protect us from the punishment of the Fire.
dan lindungilah kami dari siksa Neraka.
Amen.
Amin.
Amin ya rabbal alamin.
Amin ya rabbal alamin.
Let's dig in.
Ayo kita makan.
[Ode] Let's go.
- [Boy] Ayo. - Gas!
-Whoosh! -[Ode's mom] Get a plate for Mr. Dua.
[ibu Ode] Kasih piring ke Bapak Dua.
[exclaims] So good!
[berseru] Mantap!
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
-[Ode] Mr. Dua. -[Ode's mom] Pass the plate.
- [Ode] Bapak Dua. - [ibu Ode] Kasih piringnya.
Mom, are you excited that he's leaving home?
Mama ini kelihatan senang sekali anaknya mau keluar dari rumah, ya.
Is that why we have a feast?
Sampai bikin acara begini.
I'm not excited, I'm sad.
Tidak. Mana ada Mama senang. Mama sedih.
Think of this as
Ini juga sekaligus untuk
a prayer for your upcoming success in Jakarta.
menyusul kesuksesan kalian nanti di Jakarta.
May it go well.
Semoga lancar.
I pray for my children to always be under Allah's protection.
Mama doakan semoga anak-anak Mama ini
[in unison] Amen.
[bersamaan] Amin.
May they stay far from drugs…
Dijauhkan dari narkoba…
[Ode's mom] …and from women.
…dijauhkan dari perempuan.
-Amen. -[Ode] Amen.
- Amin. - [Ode] Amin.
No amen to that?
Kenapa kau tidak amin?
No way. What if women stay away,
Ya, tidak, lah. Bagaimana kalau kita dijauhkan dari perempuan
but we're approached by men instead?
malah didekatkan dengan laki-laki?
-Hey! -Oh my God!
- Hei! - Astaga!
See? You laughed.
Hiburan ini!
For me, I don't want that. I'd prefer women to approach me.
Tapi aku tidak mau. Aku maunya didekati perempuan.
-Whatever. -Stop joking like that.
- Ya. - Kau bercanda saja.
But where's the beef?
Tapi kenapa tidak ada daging?
We normally have beef for a feast, right?
Biasanya kalau ada acara, kita ada daging sapi.
[Ode's mom] This is plenty enough.
Sudah, lah. Ini cukup.
Beef isn't your thing, Boy.
Kau tidak cocok makan daging sapi, Boy.
No need to make a fuss.
Sudahlah, jangan banyak tingkah.
-[Boy] But beef is part of a feast… -Dad is right.
- Biasanya kalau kita perayaan… - Benar kata Bapak!
-Enough about that. -We don't like beef anyway.
- Sudahlah. - Kita memang tidak suka sapi.
Cows don't like us either, right?
Karena sapi saja tidak suka sama kita, 'kan?
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
[Boy] Nice joke. Use that in the competition.
[Boy] Lucu itu, Raim. Kau pakai nanti di kompetisi.
And get eliminated.
Supaya kau tereliminasi.
-♪ Happy birthday to you ♪ -Whose birthday is it?
- ♪ Selamat ulang tahun ♪ - Siapa ulang tahun?
♪ Happy birthday to you ♪
♪ Selamat ulang tahun ♪
[cheering, clapping]
[bersorak, tepuk tangan]
Oops. I blew it out.
Eh, tertiup.
Dad, give me your lighter.
Bapak, pinjam korek.
It went out.
Tertiup.
The wind was too strong.
Anginnya terlalu kencang.
You and your big breath.
Ya, napasmu terlalu besar.
Oh, it's your birthday?
Ulang tahun dia.
Here, go ahead. Say a prayer.
Ayo, kau tiup dulu ini. Jangan lupa berdoa.
[exclaiming]
[berseru]
-Mr. Dua, dig in. -Thank you.
- Ayo, Bapak Dua. Dimakan. - Terima kasih, ya.
You're welcome.
Sama-sama.
[indistinct chatter, clattering]
[mengobrol, kelontang alat makan]
[Ode] Time flies.
[Ode] Tidak terasa.
We've been together for a while now.
Ternyata sudah lama juga kita pacaran.
You're graduating soon,
Sekarang kau sudah mau lulus,
and busy with your organization,
lagi sibuk urus organisasi.
and I'm getting ready to leave for Jakarta.
Aku juga sudah mau ke Jakarta.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
To be honest,
Tapi, sejujurnya,
I…
aku itu…
I can't do this without you.
tidak bisa kalau tidak denganmu.
That's why I hope you understand
Makanya, aku harap kau mengerti,
why I'm doing this.
kenapa aku lakukan ini.
I understand.
Aku mengerti, kok.
I'll wait for you.
Aku tunggu kau.
I love you so much.
Aku sayang sekali denganmu.
Do you?
Masa?
-Here we go again. -[chuckles]
- Nah, mulai lagi! - [terkekeh]
I'm being serious.
Serius. Aku tidak bercanda.
Really? How serious?
Masa? Seberapa serius memang?
Two million percent.
Dua juta persen, aku serius.
-Two million? -Two million!
- Dua juta? - Dua juta!
Not convinced? Five million percent serious!
Kurang? Lima juta persen aku serius!
[chuckling]
[tertawa]
As long as
Pokoknya,
you haven't made your vow on the altar,
selama janur kuning belum melengkung di depan rumahmu,
and I'm still alive,
dan aku masih hidup di dunia ini,
I will always love you.
aku akan tetap terus cinta sama kau.
I love you too.
Aku juga sayang sama kau.
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
[gasps]
[terkesiap]
Java's garbage!
Sampah Jawa!
[laughing]
[tertawa]
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
[Ode] Yes.
- Ya. - [ayah Ode] Lagi?
Take care.
Hati-hati, ya.
Wish me luck.
Doakan.
Take care, son.
Baik-baik kau, Nak, di sana.
Yes, Mom.
Ya, Ma.
I'll miss you a lot.
Aku pasti akan rindu sekali sama Mama.
[sniffling]
[tersedu-sedu]
-Bye. -Don't forget to pray.
- Dah. - Jangan lupa salat ya, Nak.
Yes, ma'am.
Siap.
[Boy] Bye.
[Boy] Dah.
Wish me luck.
Doakan, ya.
God willing.
Insyaallah, pasti.
-[Ode's mom] Take care. -[Boy] I will.
- [ibu Ode] Kau jaga adikmu. - [Boy] Aku jaga.
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
Take care.
Baik-baik, ya, Nak.
I will.
Ya.
Quit it, Dad.
Sudahlah.
This is my last one.
Ini yang terakhir.
I promise.
Bapak janji.
Yes.
Ya.
-You take care too, Dad. -I will.
Bapak sehat-sehat, ya.
[soft laugh]
[terkekeh]
I'm going away for a while.
Izinkan aku pergi sebentar.
Okay?
Ya?
I'll be missing you.
Kau tahan kangenmu dulu.
Take care.
Hati-hati, ya.
Let me know as soon as you get there.
Nanti kalau sudah sampai, kabari, ya.
-[Ican] Take a seat in the front. -Peace be upon you.
- [Ican] Kau di depan. - Asalamualaikum.
You can sit in the back.
Di belakang saja.
What am I? A sacrificial lamb?
Aku kayak kambing kurban.
You'll still reach Jakarta.
Yang penting Abang ke Jakarta, 'kan?
You can visit Malioboro too.
Bisa jalan-jalan ke Malioboro.
Of course. Want me to get you a souvenir?
Ya, lah. Kau mau titip oleh-oleh?
I'd love that.
Ya, mau, Bang.
[Boy] What kind?
Apa?
One of those dangling things would be nice.
Gantungan bagus, itu.
Oh, like a keychain?
Oh, gantungan kunci?
No.
Bukan.
A clothes hanger. Like…
Gantungan baju, seperti hanger, begitu, Bang. Yang…
-You wouldn't get it. -[Ode] Ican, help me out here.
- Tidak paham. - [Ode] Ican, bagaimana, Can?
[Ode] Ican, I can't open the door.
Ican, bagaimana? Tidak bisa dibuka.
-[Ode] The door won't open. -[Ican] Then get in the back.
- [Ode] Tidak bisa dibuka. - [Ican] Di belakang saja.
-I'll be going. -Boy.
- Berangkat, ya. - Kakak Boy.
Make space.
Aku di belakang.
Let's be sacrificial lambs together.
Jadi kambing kurban sama-sama kita.
Okay.
Oke.
Bye.
Dah.
Take care, Mom.
Mama sehat-sehat, ya.
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
[up-tempo music playing]
[musik bersemangat]
[no audible dialog]
[dialog tanpa suara]
[Boy] Is that Monas?
[Boy] Apakah itu Monas?
-Monas! -It is!
- Monas! - Ya!
-Monas! Take a pic!
- Monas! Foto!
-The top of it is made of gold. -Gold? Really?
Emas di atasnya itu.
How do you know?
Kau tahu dari mana?
-Some guy told me. -[laughing]
- Ada mas-mas yang kasih tahu aku. - [tertawa]
[man] Bro!
[pria] Bro!
[in English] It's awesome in Minnesota.
[dalam Bahasa Inggris] Luar biasa di Minnesota.
[in English] Welcome to Jakarta. [laughs]
Selamat datang di Jakarta. [tertawa]
South Jakartan pantun!
Pantun Jaksel, lah!
[in English] Come on, let's go.
Ayo.
My man, call me Maman.
Aku My Man, panggil saja Maman.
Come on.
- Ayo. - Ya, Bang.
[in English] This is your apartment, bro.
Ini apartemen kalian.
You'll be staying here while you're in Jakarta.
Selama di Jakarta, kalian tinggal di sini.
-[in English] Okay, enjoy. -Thank you.
- Baiklah, semoga nyaman. - Terima kasih, Bang!
[exclaims in awe]
[berseru kagum]
[Ode] All right.
[Ode] Enak!
-Raim. -Hmm?
- Hei, Raim. - Ya?
Mom keeps saying that Dad smokes too much.
Mama melapor terus, katanya Bapak isap rokok banyak sekali.
Oh.
Oh.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
What are you doing?
Kau bikin apa?
Let me write a song first.
Aku mau bikin lagu dulu.
What about stand-up materials?
Kau tidak bikin materi komedi tunggal?
We can do that later.
Nanti saja, gampang itu.
[phone buzzing]
[dengung ponsel]
Hello.
Halo.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
[Ode] And upon you peace. Om swastiastu.
[Ode] Alaikum salam. Om Swastiastu.
What are you doing, Three Letters?
Lagi apa, Tiga Huruf?
I'm peeling onions right now. What are you doing?
Lagi mengupas bawang saja, kau lagi apa?
I just finished the ashr prayer.
Aku baru selesai asar, ini.
Guess what?
Kau tahu?
I live on the twentieth floor,
Aku tinggal di lantai 20.
so my prayers get to the heavens faster than yours.
Jadi, kalau aku berdoa, sudah pasti lebih cepat tiba di langitnya dari kau.
No way. Prayers reach the heavens equally from anywhere.
Mana ada. Doa dari mana saja juga sama saja sampainya.
But my prayers get there faster
Tapi yang aku pasti lebih cepat sampai, 'kan?
because you're on the ground.
Kau doa dari bawah.
That's not true.
Tidak juga.
With all the pollution, your prayer might get lost.
Malah punyamu bisa tersesat soalnya banyak polusi sama debu.
I guess so.
Ya juga, ya.
Let me know when you're not busy.
Nanti kasih tahu, ya, kalau lagi tidak sibuk.
I'd like to video call.
Aku mau panggilan video.
[Ode makes teasing noises]
[Ode berseru menggoda]
You miss this handsome face already?
Kau sudah rindu dengan muka gantengku ini?
Handsome face?
Muka ganteng apa?
More like a coral reef to me.
Terumbu karang, maksudnya?
We are out of incense.
Mang, dupa sudah habis, ya.
Yes, Mom.
Ya, Meme.
I'm gonna go help my mom.
Aku bantu Meme dulu, ya.
Call me later.
Kabari, ya.
Okay.
Oke.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Hey, you ready?
- Hei, kau sudah siap? - Sudah.
With that bag?
Kau bawa tas itu?
[groans]
[berseru]
You look like a debt collector. We're gonna party.
Kau seperti penagih utang. Kita ini mau pesta.
-You don't get Jakarta at all. -What party?
- Tidak paham Jakarta kau ini. - Pesta apa?
People's party!
Pesta rakyat!
People's party?
Pesta rakyat?
Who was that? Raim?
Siapa itu, Raim?
What is he doing in Jakarta?
Kenapa dia ke Jakarta?
If he was committed, he wouldn't have left.
Kalau dia serius denganmu, dia tidak akan pergi.
Men are quick to stray,
Laki-laki memang begitu, hatinya cepat berubah.
especially in a city like Jakarta.
Apalagi di kota besar seperti Jakarta.
You should learn from your sister Kadek's experience.
Seharusnya kau 'kan belajar dari pengalaman Mbokmu, Kadek itu, lo.
After getting married, she barely comes home.
Setelah menikah, dia jarang sekali pulang.
I can count her visits with one hand.
Bisa dihitung sama jari berapa kali dia main ke sini.
Okay?
Ya?
[somber music playing]
[musik sendu]
You know how Mom is.
Meme memang begitu.
Who'd want to visit if she keeps acting like that?
Siapa yang betah main kalau sikapnya seperti itu?
Are you really sure about Raim?
Tapi kau memangnya sudah yakin sama Raim?
Think it over.
Coba dipikir-pikir dulu, ya.
Do you want to end up like me?
Mau nasibmu seperti Mbok Dek?
Exciting, isn't it?
Enak, 'kan? Seru, 'kan?
Yeah.
Seru, Bang.
[Maman] I'll take care of everything!
Pokoknya aku yang urus!
[Maman] Order up!
- Pesan! - Oke.
A glass of water.
Air putih saja.
Make it two.
- Air putih juga. - Yah…
This is Jakarta.
Ya, begini lah Jakarta, Bro.
[exclaims] Hey. Istighfar, Boy!
[berseru] Istigfar kau, Boy.
That's sinful!
Dosamu banyak, itu!
-Take it easy. -Come on.
- Sedikit saja, lah. - Ya ampun.
You may say that now, Raim,
Sekarang kau bisa bilang begitu, Im.
but once she sits next to you, you'll freeze up.
Nanti, kalau dia duduk di sebelahmu, kau diam tidak berkutik.
[giggling]
[tertawa]
Don't worry.
Tenang saja, Bang.
I have a girlfriend.
Aku ini sudah punya pacar.
-You do? -Yup.
- Kau sudah punya pacar? - Sudah.
Oh no.
Yah… Tapi kau harus ingat, Im.
relationships and family are private matters.
Urusan pacar, keluarga, itu urusan pribadi.
Keep them out of your profession, or you'll lose focus.
Jangan dicampur sama urusan profesi, nanti kau tidak fokus.
That's not it.
Hei, bukan begitu, Bang.
Rest assured. I'm still single.
Tenang saja, kalau aku tidak ada pacar.
No wonder.
Oh, pantas.
But Raim's girl is a good kid.
Tapi Raim juga punya pacar baik, kok.
She's kind and won't be a bother.
Orangnya penurut, tidak akan ganggu.
We're here to focus on our careers.
Kita ke sini memang datang untuk mengejar karier.
-[chuckling] -He's right.
- [tertawa] - Ya.
That means you're CWP.
- Berarti TTP, dong. - Apa itu?
Careful with your partner.
Takut-Takut Pacar.
Not CMP?
Aku kira TTP.
What's that?
Apa itu?
Collecting more partners.
Tambal-Tambal Pacar.
[laughing] I like that.
[tertawa] Boleh juga.
But you're MTP.
Kau yang TTP.
What's that?
Apa itu?
Missing the punchline! Not funny!
Tidak Tahu Punchline! Tidak lucu!
[laughing]
[tertawa]
You're from Wakatobi too?
Mas ini dari Wakatobi juga?
You look like a coral reef.
Soalnya mirip terumbu karang juga ini.
After a bombing.
Yang dibom.
Ouch.
Aduh…
Messed up.
Hancur sekali.
[crowd laughing, clapping]
[audiens tertawa, tepuk tangan]
We're good, though. Peace.
Berteman kita. Damai.
Listen, guys.
Nah, Teman-Teman.
For us Wakatobi people, breakups are hard to move on from.
Kita, orang Wakatobi ini, kalau sudah pacaran dan putus,
Why?
Kenapa?
Because everyone looks the same!
Karena semuanya mirip!
Identical!
Sama. Rata!
No difference.
Tidak ada bedanya.
-So after a breakup… -Komang.
- Kalau kita habis putus dari pacar… - Komang.
Komang.
Komang.
[Komang's mom] Komang.
[ibu Komang] Mang.
-[laughter from TV] -[Komang's mom] Komang.
- [suara tawa dari TV] - Komang.
Komang.
Mang.
Turn down the TV volume a bit.
Makanya kalau menonton, jangan keras-keras volumenya.
You didn't even notice we had a guest.
Sampai tidak dengar kalau ada tamu.
It's okay, Auntie.
Tidak apa-apa, Bu.
-I'm sorry, Arya. -It's okay, she was watching TV.
- Aduh, maaf ya, Arya. - Dia sedang menonton.
-What did you buy? -Incense.
- Beli apa kau? - [Ode di televisi] Oke, baiklah.
[Komang's mom] Do you need some?
[ibu Komang] Darimu, Arya?
But if you're ever low on incense, let me know.
Tapi besok kalau habis dupanya, bilang saja.
I have a lot at home. I'll bring some over.
Aku punya banyak soalnya. Nanti aku bawakan.
[Ode on TV] Finding girls is like finding fish in the sea.
[Ode di televisi] Mencari gadis sama seperti mencari ikan di laut.
-If you don't get it… -[Arya] Komang.
- Jika tidak dapat… - Komang.
[show continues indistinctly]
- …kita beli ikan di pasar. - Aku boleh bicara sebentar, bisa?
[laughter on TV, show continuing indistinctly]
- [suara tawa di televisi] - Walaupun sudah dikasih es…
Okay.
Bisa.
-Excuse me, Auntie. -Okay.
- Ke depan dulu, ya, Bu. - Ya.
[show continuing indistinctly]
[Ode] Akhirnya, setelah itu aku pulang. Aku…
[Arya] Hello.
- [Arya] Beli. - Ya.
-Hello, Arya. -Hello.
- Arya. Ya. - [Komang] Halo, Beli.
-Sit down, Komang. -Thank you.
- Duduk, Arya, Komang. - Terima kasih, Beli.
What's up? What do you want to talk about?
Kenapa kau mengajak aku ke sini? Mau mengobrol apa?
Are you still setting up your tutoring place tomorrow?
Kau besok jadi tidak buat tempat pembukaan lesmu itu?
Yeah.
Jadi.
Let me help with photos or anything else.
Aku bantu, ya. Mungkin, buat foto?
Sure.
Ya, boleh saja.
If you don't mind.
Kalau mau.
I don't mind.
Mau, lah.
I'm always available for you 24/7.
Buat kau, aku selalu siap 24 jam.
[chuckles awkwardly]
[tertawa canggung]
I asked Ola to help.
- Tidak. Aku sudah minta bantuan Ola. - [denting ponsel]
[phone dings]
Insyaallah dia bisa… bantu.
[somber music]
[musik sendu]
[Arya] Raim?
[Arya] Raim?
Yeah.
Ya.
Hang on.
Sebentar, ya.
-[phone buzzing] -[Ode] What do I do?
- [dengung ponsel] - [Ode] Aku harus bagaimana sekarang?
-[Boy] Easy, there. -You can't leave.
- [Boy] Sudah, hei. - Jangan pergi.
This is just how it is.
Memang sudah jalannya begini.
I know I didn't perform my best.
Sudah. Aku juga tadi tampil memang kurang.
You pursue your dreams here.
Kau kejar mimpimu di sini,
I'll look after our parents back at home.
aku jaga Bapak dengan Mama di kampung.
This is the way.
Harus begitu.
So you can focus here.
Supaya kau juga fokus di sini.
Don't worry about me.
Kau tak usah pikirkan aku lagi.
-[sighs] How can I not worry about you? -There, there.
- Bagaimana aku tidak pikirkan? - Sudahlah.
-[Boy] It's okay. -[phone buzzing]
- [Boy] Tak apa. - [dengung ponsel]
-[voicemail] The number you are calling… -[clicks tongue]
- [pesan suara] Nomor yang Anda tuju… - [berdecak]
[somber music playing]
[musik sendu]
After spending weeks in Jakarta…
Beberapa minggu aku di Jakarta,
They say Jakarta is hot, but Wakatobi is even worse.
orang bilang Jakarta panas, padahal di Wakatobi juga lebih panas.
It's like every house gets its own sun.
Di sana itu, satu rumah satu matahari.
-[laughing] -[Ode] It's so hot…
- [tertawa] - [Ode] Begitu panasnya…
[Ode] I can't fail, Ade.
[Ode] Aku tidak boleh gagal, Ade.
You said it yourself.
Kau yang bilang sendiri, bukan?
If you dream big,
Kalau kita punya mimpi tinggi,
keep your spirit high, don't let it hang low like a clothesline.
nyali pun juga harus tinggi, jangan cuma sampai tali jemuran.
[Komang] I'll always support you from here.
[Komang] Aku selalu dukung kau di sini.
God wouldn't bring you this far just to make you fail.
Tuhan tidak mungkin bawa kau sejauh itu cuma untuk gagal.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
I wonder how Boy is doing.
Kakak Boy bagaimana, ya?
I have to fight on my own now.
Aku harus berjuang sendiri sekarang.
[Komang] Ode.
[Komang] Ode.
You always fight your own battles.
Perjuangan itu dari awal memang punya kau sendiri.
Others may walk alongside you,
Orang lain mungkin bisa menemanimu jalan,
but no one can walk in your place.
tapi tidak ada yang bisa gantikan kau berjalan.
What are you doing?
Kau lagi apa?
I'm sending out an echolocation signal. Can you hear it?
Aku lagi kirim sinyal ekolokasi. Dengar, tidak?
What? Are you a dolphin?
Ekolokasi? Memangnya kau lumba-lumba?
What?
Apa itu?
My way of saying I miss you.
Ungkapan rindu.
[Ode] Hang in there.
[Ode] Sabar, ya.
This is part of our journey.
Ini bagian dari perjalanan kita.
I'll get even busier,
Ke depannya, aku akan lebih sibuk.
but I have to succeed.
Aku harus berhasil.
[Komang] I understand.
[Komang] Ya, aku mengerti.
I'll always support you from here.
Aku selalu dukung kau di sini, kok.
Raim!
Im!
Meet Natasha, a music producer.
Ini Natasha, dia produser musik. Kenalkan.
Oh, hi.
Oh, aku…
-Natasha. -Raim.
- Natasha. - Raim.
Stay calm. Keep your spirits up.
Sudah, tenang saja. Tetap semangat.
Bro.
Bro.
-How are you? -I'm good.
- Apa kabar? - Sehat, Bro.
-See you. -Bye.
- Duluan, ya. - Ya.
[gasps] Man.
[terkesiap] Bang.
Was that Afgan?
Itu Afgan?
-Yeah. -The real Afgan?
- Ya. - Afgan itu, Bang?
-The singer, yeah. Yeah. -He's your friend?
Ya, penyanyi.
Don't lie. He's your friend?
Jangan bohong. Itu benar temanmu?
-Yes, the Afgan. -That's crazy.
- Ya. Afgan. - Gila!
[Ola] Okay, so…
[Ola] Kalau sekarang…
Does anyone know the English word for "bunga"?
Ada yang tahu bahasa Inggrisnya "bunga"?
[kids in English] Flower!
[anak-anak dalam bahasa Inggris] Flower!
Good.
Benar.
Rini, what flower do you like?
Rini suka bunga apa?
[Rini] Sunflower.
[Rini] Bunga matahari.
[Ola] What's that in English?
Kalau bunga matahari bahasa Inggrisnya apa?
[Rini in English] Sunflower.
[Rini dalam bahasa Inggris] Sunflower.
-I like sunflowers too. -Good job.
- Aku juga suka bunga matahari. - Pintar.
Does anyone know the English word for "hujan"?
Kalau bahasa Inggrisnya "hujan" ada yang tahu?
-Me! -Rain!
- Aku! - Rain!
-Good. -Usually, when it rains,
- Benar. - Kalau aku biasanya pulang-pergi,
I like to get soaked in the rain.
kalau hujan aku biasanya mandi hujan.
-[Ola] Really? -When I go home.
- Oh, ya? - Kalau pulang-pergi.
-[Ola] Can you do that? -Yeah.
- Memang diperbolehkan? - Boleh.
-[Ola] Don't you get in trouble? -But I must change first.
- Tidak dimarahi sampai di rumah? - Tapi ganti baju dulu.
[Ola] Oh.
Oh.
Let's go.
Sudah. Ayo.
Are you happy being a Muslim?
Kau senang tidak jadi Muslim?
I feel nothing but gratitude so far.
Alhamdulillah, sejauh ini aku bersyukur.
Why are you asking that?
Kenapa tiba-tiba kau tanya begitu?
No reason. Just curious.
Tidak apa-apa. Ingin tahu saja.
My dad said
Abaku pernah bilang,
that faith requires conviction.
kalau keyakinan itu menjalaninya harus yakin.
If you hesitate, then it's no longer belief,
Kalau ragu, namanya bukan keyakinan, tapi keraguan.
How are you and Raim?
Kau bagaimana sama Raim?
We're fine.
Tidak bagaimana-bagaimana. Baik-baik saja.
I figured.
Pantas.
I wish someone would fight over me too.
Aku ingin juga diperebutkan.
Like…
Kayak…
[whines playfully]
[memekik]
"Stop! Don't fight over me."
"Jangan! Jangan, Mas, jangan perebutkan aku."
"I can choose for myself!"
Kayak, "Aku juga punya pilihan sendiri!"
-"Don't touch me! No!" -[woman] Ola!
- "Jangan sentuh aku. Tidak mau!" - [wanita] Ola!
Get my prayer gown! I want to pray.
Mukena aku! Aku juga mau salat.
Hang on.
Sebentar.
Ade.
Ade.
Let's go.
Ayo.
[Ode] What do I do now?
[Ode] Sekarang aku harus bagaimana, Bang?
You're already on the right track, Raim.
Sebenarnya, jalan yang kau ambil itu sudah benar, Im.
SUCU is just a stepping stone.
SUCU hanya untuk batu loncatan saja.
[in English] It's like a… jump stone.
[dalam bahasa Inggris] Seperti… jump stone.
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
Right?
Ya, 'kan, Bang?
Huh? What do you mean?
Apa?
See? He agrees.
Lihat. Abang itu saja setuju.
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
Everyone should first be familiar with Raim Laode.
Yang penting, semua orang sudah kenal dulu sama Raim Laode.
So I shouldn't go home yet?
Jadi, aku jangan pulang dulu?
Yeah. You can't just go back and forth between Sulawesi and Jakarta.
Ya, Im. Masa kau mau bolak-balik Sulawesi dan Jakarta?
Three days in Jakarta is barely more than a seminar trip.
Kalau kau di Jakarta cuma tiga hari, itu namanya kau ikut seminar.
A week?
Kalau seminggu?
Study tour!
Karyawisata!
A month?
Kalau sebulan?
Enough questions! Sit.
Kebanyakan tanya kau. Sudah, duduk.
Hey.
Hei.
[Maman] There she is. Nat!
[Maman] Nah, itu dia orangnya. Nat!
-How are you? Sorry you had to wait. -I'm doing great, Nat.
- Apa kabar? - Sehat.
How are you?
- Sehat, 'kan? - Tentu sehat. Halo. Hai.
[stammers]
[tergagap]
[chuckling] How are you?
[terkekeh] Apa kabar?
-[stammers] I'm good. -Okay.
- [terbata-bata] Baik. Alhamdulillah. - Oke.
-Sit down. So I let her know that…
- Duduk. Jadi, aku sudah jelaskan ke dia…
…you play guitar and write songs.
…kalau kau suka main gitar dan suka menciptakan lagu.
She used to manage Ebiet G. Ade.
Kemarin Ebiet G. Ade diproduseri sama dia, dan sekarang jadi Ebiet G. Abang.
[cackling]
[tertawa]
That's too much.
Bisa sekali. Berlebihan.
Let her check out your songs.
Sudah, dengarkan lagu-lagu yang sudah iseng kau rekam itu sama dia.
It's not finished, though.
Belum selesai itu, Bang.
As long as there's some sound in it.
Yang penting ada suaranya.
Okay.
Ya sudah.
Do you mind wearing this?
Pakai ini tidak apa-apa, 'kan?
I don't mind.
Tidak apa-apa.
-Here. -Okay, thanks.
- Maaf. - Oke. Terima kasih.
[faint music playing over phone]
♪ Sebab kau terlalu indah ♪
It's good.
Bagus.
Really good.
Bagus!
Nice demo.
Bagus demonya.
-Really? -Mm-hmm.
- Serius? - Ya.
When can we start recording?
Kapan kita bisa rekaman?
That was quick.
Cepat sekali.
Um… I'm ready anytime.
[bergumam] Aku siap kapan saja.
[in English] Okay, good.
Oke, bagus.
[Maman in English] Yes! Okay.
[Maman berseru] Ya, baiklah! Kita pesan dulu.
Here.
Nah.
I've informed Maman that we usually take care of distribution.
Tadi juga sudah bilang sama Maman
[in English] But we're open for discussion.
[dalam bahasa Inggris] Tapi kami bersedia diskusi.
Got it.
Siap.
By the way, you live in Jakarta, right?
Oh, ya. Kau tinggal di Jakarta, 'kan?
Sometimes, I travel between Jakarta and Baubau.
Aku kadang suka pulang dan pergi antara Jakarta dan Baubau.
And Baubau is in…?
Baubau? Baubau itu di…
Sulawesi.
Sulawesi.
That's tough.
Akan berat itu.
[Komang] Did your producer get to hear the song?
[Komang] Lalu, kau sudah kasih dengar sama produsermu itu?
[Ode] Yeah. She likes it.
Sudah. Dia suka.
I must finish this song soon.
Aku harus cepat-cepat selesaikan lagu ini.
So I can't go home yet.
Makanya belum bisa pulang dulu ke kampung.
Mm…
[menggumam]
It's okay.
Ya sudah, tidak apa-apa.
This is your moment.
Itu kesempatanmu juga.
Is your producer a guy?
Produsermu laki-laki?
A girl.
Perempuan.
How about you?
Kau sendiri?
Haven't you been close with Arya lately?
Bukannya sering habiskan waktu sama Arya sekarang?
I'm not.
Tidak sering.
But you're with Arya more than you're with me, right?
Tapi lebih sering habiskan waktu sama Arya daripada sama aku, 'kan?
You're not any better.
Sama saja denganmu.
You're always with your producer.
Kau juga lebih sering menghabiskan waktu sama produsermu itu.
Ade.
Ade,
We are dating,
kita memang pacaran,
but that doesn't mean you're tied down.
tapi yang namanya pacaran itu tidak mengikat.
If you find someone better,
Kalau kau bertemu yang lebih baik,
I won't stop you.
aku tidak akan melarang.
Go ahead.
Silakan.
[somber music playing]
[musik muram]
What do you mean?
Apa maksudmu?
That doesn't sound like a relationship.
Kalau seperti itu, seperti bukan orang pacaran.
Do you want to break up?
Kau mau kita putus?
Maybe that's for the best.
Mungkin itu yang terbaik.
Hello?
Halo?
Ade…
Ade…
[heavy breathing]
[napas berat]
[sniffling]
[tersedu-sedu]
[Ibu] Komang.
[ibu Komang] Komang.
Why have you been ordering incense online?
Kenapa jadi sering beli dupa lewat daring?
[Komang] It's simpler that way.
Biar lebih mudah saja.
Aren't you going to shower? I thought Raim was coming.
Terus kok belum mandi? Katanya Raim mau datang.
He's not.
Tidak jadi.
When is he coming?
Terus, kapan mau datang?
Ode has things to do in Jakarta.
Ode masih ada urusan di Jakarta.
Oh, Komang.
Komang, Komang.
Be more realistic, won't you?
Cobalah realistis sedikit.
Look at what's in front of you
Lihat apa yang ada di depan mata saja, bukan yang jauh-jauh di sana.
When Arya is here,
Arya itu kalau lagi di sini,
he stops by every day to help us out.
setiap hari datang bantu-bantu keluarga kita.
He's kind, Komang.
Baik dia itu, Mang.
Yes, Mom.
Ya, Bu.
Why not see where it goes?
Kenapa tidak dicoba dulu?
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
Kadek moved with her husband.
Mbok Kadek sudah ikut sama suaminya.
If I'm with Arya,
Komang kalau ikut sama Arya,
he'll take me to Kalimantan.
Komang dibawa ke Kalimantan sama Arya.
You'll be all alone here, and even lonelier.
Meme di sini sendirian, makin kesepian lagi.
If you're with Raim, he will take you to Jakarta too.
Kau juga sama Raim, kau nanti dibawa juga ke Jakarta.
Either way, I'll be alone.
Sama saja, Meme juga akan sendiri nantinya.
At least if you're with Arya, I'll feel more at ease.
Setidaknya kalau kau sama Arya, Meme itu lebih tenang, Sayang.
Okay?
Ya?
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
I guess love by itself isn't enough.
Ternyata cinta saja tidak cukup, ya.
Do you know this saying?
Kau pernah dengar pepatah, tidak?
A woman is always faced with two choices.
Katanya, perempuan itu selalu dihadapkan dengan dua pilihan.
Accepting the man who proposes to them,
Menerima lelaki yang meminangnya,
or waiting for the man they love to do so.
atau menunggu lelaki yang mencintainya untuk meminangnya.
But I get to choose my soulmate, right?
Tapi, siapa pun jodohku, aku bisa pilih, 'kan?
I think
Kalau itu,
that's up to fate to decide.
tergantung takdirnya, bukan?
Rini.
Rini.
Are you done playing?
Sudah, ya, mainnya?
Yes, Auntie.
Sudah, Tante.
You can take off your hijab if it's hot.
Kalau panas, tidak apa-apa, dibuka dulu saja jilbabnya.
No, my mom says I look prettier with a hijab.
Tidak mau, Tante. Kata Mama, aku lebih cantik kalau memakai jilbab.
You are pretty, Rini.
Ya, Rini cantik sekali.
-Let's go home, then. -[Rini] Yeah.
- Ayo kita pulang. - Ayo.
Good girl.
Begitu, ya? Cantik.
Say what to Auntie?
Bilang apa sama Tante?
-Bye, Auntie Komang. -Bye, Rini, Ola.
- Dah, Tante Komang. - Dah, Rini, Ola.
Auntie.
Ibu.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
And upon you peace.
Wa'alaikumsalam warahmatullahi wabarakatuh.
What are you doing here?
Sedang apa Ibu di sini?
My husband is not doing too well.
Bapak sedang tidak baik-baik saja, Nak.
[coughing]
[batuk]
Please pray for his recovery.
Doakan, ya, semoga Bapak cepat sehat.
[somber music playing]
[musik sendu]
[Ode's mom] Ade.
[ibu Ode] Ade.
I'm at a loss.
Sebenarnya Ibu itu bingung.
Whenever Dad asks
Kalau Bapak bertanya,
about Ode,
"Apa kabarnya Ode?
how Ode is doing,
Bagaimana keadaannya?"
I don't know how to answer.
Ibu tidak bisa menjawab.
I think
Sepertinya,
he really misses Ode.
Bapak rindu sekali sama Ode.
Do you still keep in touch often?
Kalian masih sering berhubungan?
If you do,
Kalau nanti berhubungan,
tell him to come home.
kasih tahu suruh pulang.
His father misses him.
Bapaknya rindu.
[Arya] I've talked to your mom.
[Arya] Aku sudah bicara sama Meme.
I want us to take the next step. I want to marry you.
Aku mau serius sama kau, De. Aku mau nikah sama kau.
What are you even saying?
Kenapa tiba-tiba seperti ini?
I know this can't come as a surprise to you.
Tidak tiba-tiba, De. Aku yakin dari dulu kau tahu.
I know you and Raim are a thing,
Aku tunggu kau selama ini sama Raim, De,
but I can't bear to see you like this.
tapi tidak tega aku lihat kau seperti ini terus.
You're precious, Ade. You deserve certainty.
Ade, kau terlalu berarti untuk menunggu sesuatu yang tidak pasti.
And you have me here. A certainty.
Sementara ada aku di sini yang pasti.
Ade.
Ade.
You're wasting your time.
Waktumu terbuang, De.
I hate seeing you feeling down because of Raim.
Ade, aku tidak bisa lihat kau sedih terus karena Raim.
Ade.
Ade.
Ade, give me a chance to make you happy.
Ade, izinkan aku membuatmu bahagia.
Let me ease the pain that Raim left behind.
Biar aku jadi obat sakit hatinya kau sama Raim.
[tender, somber music]
[musik lembut, sendu]
Dear.
Pak.
Wake up. It's time to pray.
Bangun, salat dulu, Pak.
And… there it is.
Nah… Itu dia.
-[in English] Easy listening. -[phone buzzing]
- [dalam bahasa Inggris] Enak didengar. - Ya.
-See? -Magic tricks?
- Bisa, 'kan? - Sulap ya?
Not witchcraft.
Yang penting bukan sihir.
-Thanks. -[phone keeps buzzing]
- Terima kasih. - [dengung ponsel]
So, where were we?
Hei, sampai mana tadi?
Uh, about the drums.
[bergumam] Kau lagi membicarakan drum.
Right.
Oh, ya.
If possible, add a touch of trumpet too.
Nanti juga kalau boleh ditambah sedikit, kasih terompet begitu?
We can arrange that.
Itu bisa diatur.
Okay. But just at one point.
Ya, tapi pas di satu titik saja.
[phone buzzing]
[dengung ponsel]
We'll sort it out back at the office…
Berarti nanti kita pulang, ke kantor, langsung susun aja ke…
-Excuse me. -Okay.
- Sebentar, ya. - Ya.
[Ode sighs]
[Ode menghela napas]
[Boy] Peace be upon you.
[Boy] Asalamualaikum.
Hello. Peace be upon you.
Halo. Alaikum salam.
What's up? I'm in a meeting.
Ada apa, Boy? Aku sedang rapat.
[sniffling] Be patient, stay strong.
[terisak-isak] Tabah ya, kuatkan dirimu.
Dad has passed away, Raim.
Bapak sudah meninggal, Raim.
[sobbing] Dad has passed away, Raim.
[tersedu-sedu]
[background music fades]
[latar musik memudar]
Our dad has passed away.
Ayah kita sudah meninggal.
Our dad is gone, Raim.
Ayah kita sudah meninggal, Raim.
What will we do?
Bagaimana nasib kita?
Please come home.
Pulanglah, Raim.
["Bersenja Gurau" by Raim Laode playing]
["Bersenja Gurau" oleh Raim Laode bermain]
Ode, my condolences.
Ode, aku turut berduka cita, ya.
[Ode] Thank you.
[Ode] Terima kasih.
Stay strong.
Kuat, ya.
[indistinct prayers]
[bacaan doa samar]
["Bersenja Gurau" by Raim Laode continues playing]
♪ Selalu ♪
[Ode] Let's wash the motorcycle together.
Kita cuci motor sama-sama, Pak.
I'll wash your motorcycle every day, I promise.
Aku akan cucikan motor Bapak setiap hari. Aku janji, Pak.
I swear to Allah.
Demi Allah, aku janji.
I will never sulk in front of you again.
Aku tidak akan pasang muka cemberut lagi di depan Bapak.
Wake up, Dad.
Bangun, Pak.
Wake up!
Pak! Bangun!
Raim, let it go.
Ikhlaskan Bapak, Raim. Ikhlas.
I can't, Boy!
Tidak mungkin, Kakak Boy!
You promised you'd take care of him.
Kau janji akan jaga Bapak, 'kan?
You promised.
Mana janjimu?
[Ode] Right?
[Ode] Ya, 'kan?
[sobbing] He's gone, Boy!
[tersedu-sedu] Bapak sudah tidak ada, Kakak Boy!
Boy!
Kakak Boy!
Everything in life comes in pairs.
Hidup itu selalu berpasangan
We complete each other.
dan saling melengkapi.
[scoffs]
[mencemooh]
Even smoking has to be philosophical for you?
Bapak ini cuma merokok saja pakai berfilosofi segala.
["Bersenja Gurau" by Raim Laode continues playing]
♪ Dan akan kembali pada-Nya ♪
[song ends]
♪ Jadi pelukan ternyaman untukmu ♪
[Ode] I don't think I've told you,
[Ode] Aku belum cerita sama kau, ya?
but I used to play here with my dad when I was a kid.
Tempat ini, dulu tempat aku bermain sama Bapak waktu kecil.
I just realized…
Aku baru sadar
how much I missed your smile.
aku rindu sekali sama senyumanmu itu.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
[Komang] I know this is hard for you.
Aku tahu, pasti ada di posisimu ini berat.
[sniffling]
[tersedu-sedu]
But from my own experience
Tapi dari pengalamanku sama
with my dad's passing…
dengan meninggalnya bapakku.
the grief
Seiring berjalannya waktu,
will ease over time.
perasaan ini akan memudar.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
Thinking about it, my life is quite ironic.
Hidup aku ini lucu juga kalau aku lihat-lihat.
I thought
Aku pikir,
we could choose our soulmates.
kita bisa pilih jodoh kita sendiri.
But some things are just beyond my control.
Ternyata ada hal lain juga yang tidak bisa aku kontrol.
This is one of them.
Ini salah satunya.
No matter how far I go…
Sejauh apa pun aku melangkah,
it always leads back to you.
tetap kau yang menjadi ujungnya.
[Ode] Now we share something in common.
Sekarang kita satu sama, ya?
[soft laugh]
[Ode terkekeh]
Our dads are playing cards in heaven.
Bapak kita pasti sedang main kartu di Surga.
That's for sure.
Sudah hafal aku. [terkekeh]
[Ode chuckles]
[terkekeh]
Are they in the same heaven, do you think?
Mereka di surga yang sama tidak, ya?
[tender music playing]
[musik lembut]
[deep breaths]
[tarikan napas panjang]
Can you get it off?
Bisa?
-I can't. -Let me.
- Tidak bisa. - Sini.
Sorry.
Maaf.
Let me say hi to your mom.
Oh, ya. Aku mau pamit sama Ibu dulu.
I feel bad for keeping you out this late.
Tidak enak aku membawamu sampai malam begini.
It's fine. She's probably asleep anyway.
Tidak usah, tidak apa-apa. Paling dia sudah tidur juga.
You should go home.
Pulang saja duluan.
At least let me walk you home.
Tapi biarkanlah aku setidaknya antar kau sampai ke depan rumahmu dulu.
Okay.
Oke.
I haven't been here in a while.
Sudah lama sekali tidak ke sini.
Feeling nostalgic?
Kangen, ya?
Yeah.
Kangen.
-[nearby door opens] -I miss praying here.
- [suara pintu dibuka] - Aku kangen salat di sini.
Gosh, Komang! Where have you been all night?
Aduh, Komang! Dari mana ini sampai malam?
You didn't answer my calls!
Telepon tidak diangkat-angkat!
You haven't told Raim?
Belum bilang kau sama Raim?
-Mom. I was… -[Komang's mom] This girl…
Ibu, aku tadi…
-Hey… -[Komang exhales shakily]
- Hei… - [Komang terengah-engah]
-[Komang's mom] Komang! -[Ode] What's going on?
- [ibu Komang] Komang! - [Ode] Ada apa ini?
[Komang breathing shakily]
[Komang bernapas berat]
[breathing deeply]
[menghela napas]
My mom accepted Arya's proposal.
Meme terima lamaran dari Arya.
I've been meaning to tell you,
Aku mau kasih tahu kau ini,
but I couldn't find the right moment.
cuma dari kemarin tidak sempat ketemu waktu yang pas.
The right moment?
"Waktu yang pas"?
There is no right moment for this.
Tidak ada waktu yang pas untuk bicarakan hal ini, Ade.
When did he propose?
Kapan Arya melamar?
A week or two ago.
Satu, dua minggu yang lalu.
Why do you ask?
Kenapa memangnya?
We broke up.
Kita sudah tidak ada hubungan lagi.
But if you've said yes to Arya, it's all over!
Tapi kalau kau sudah terima lamaran Arya, habis sudah!
My mom accepted Arya's proposal, not me!
Aku belum terima lamaran dari Arya, Meme yang terima!
I haven't given him my answer.
Aku belum bilang apa-apa! Memang dia bilang…
He said he's serious, but I haven't accepted it.
dia mau serius, tapi aku belum terima.
-So why didn't you turn him down? -Why should I?
- Terus kenapa tidak kau tolak, Ade? - Kenapa aku tolak?
You're never there for me, Ode!
Kau itu tidak pernah ada buat aku, Ode!
You're always busy with your own thing!
Kau tidak pernah ada! Kau sibuk sama duniamu sendiri!
You're making me lose my faith in you.
Kau bikin aku ragu, tahu?
Now I have a chance to make my mom happy.
Aku ini sekarang punya kesempatan buat bikin Meme bahagia.
It's my dream!
Mimpiku!
But your mother…
Tapi… Tapi ibumu…
Your mother won't approve of me if I'm not settled.
Ibumu juga, 'kan, yang tidak mau kalau aku belum sukses?
But I can do it now.
Tapi sekarang aku bisa, Ade.
I can make you happy.
Aku bisa bahagiakan kau!
I don't need empty words.
Tidak usah bicara bahagiakan aku!
If you mean it, show me so that I can believe!
Kalau memang kau mau bahagiakan aku, kau yakinkan aku!
Believe that we belong together!
Yakinkan kalau kita bisa sama-sama!
But you know this is hard right now, Ade!
Tapi kau tahu lawanku ini berat sekali, Ade!
Because I must get
Aku harus melawan restu.
your mother's blessing…
Restu ibumu.
and challenge the heavens.
Dan aku juga harus bertarung dengan yang ada di langit.
That's it?
Sudah?
Is that all?
Segitu saja?
Have you given up the fight?
Sudah habis energimu untuk berjuang?
You won't fight for me?
Untuk perjuangkan aku?
Fate's path…
Satu garis takdir,
cannot be scripted by two pens.
itu tidak mungkin ditulis oleh dua pena.
[sighs]
["Ekspektasi" oleh Aruma dan Raim Laode bermain]
What's wrong?
Kenapa kau?
Hmm?
♪ Terlalu banyak mengharapkanmu ♪
It's late.
Sudah malam ini.
Let's go inside.
Kita masuk, yuk.
-[sniffling] -Come on.
- [tersedu-sedu] - Ayo.
[Imam] Allahu akbar.
[Imam] Allahu Akbar.
[Imam] Allahu akbar.
[Imam] Allahu Akbar.
[Mr. Dua] Raim.
[Pak Dua] Raim.
Our soulmate, death, and fortune
Jodoh, kematian, dan rezeki, semua di tangan Allah.
Our duty is to pursue them.
Tugas kita menjemputnya.
If you seek fortune, head to the capital.
Kalau kau ingin rezeki, kau ke ibu kota.
Pursue it there.
Jemput rezekimu di sana.
If you want death,
Kalau kau mau mati,
jump off a bridge.
kau loncat dari jembatan.
You'll find death.
Kau mati.
If you seek your soulmate,
Tapi kalau kau mau jodoh,
go to her.
jemput dia.
Pray for her.
Doakan dia.
Do you believe?
Kau percaya, tidak?
Mr. Dua.
Bapak Dua.
I got you a little something.
Bawa ini. Ada oleh-oleh sedikit.
Mashaallah.
Masyaallah.
[Boy] These are breadfruit biscuits.
Ini biskuit dengan sukun.
Ade brought them when she visited yesterday.
Ade kemarin datang jenguk Bapak, dia bawakan ini.
[Mr. Dua] Praise God. I'll see you later, then.
[Pak Dua] Alhamdulillah. Aku pulang dulu, ya.
-Peace be upon you. -An upon you peace. Take care.
- Asalamualaikum. - Alaikum salam. Hati-hati.
Really?
Benarkah?
What?
"Benar" apa?
Come on.
Itu.
So much for being a good brother.
Kau ini katanya kakak yang baik, tapi tidak paham juga.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
What?
Apa?
Ade came here a lot?
- Ade sering ke sini? - Oh.
Yeah, she visited a lot.
Sering. Sering datang ke sini.
But don't get the wrong idea.
Tapi kami berdua tidak ada apa-apa. Kau jangan curiga.
Who said she was into you?
Percaya dirimu itu. Memang dia mau sama kau?
-I guess not. -[phone keeps dinging]
- Ya juga. - [denting ponsel]
See?
- Itu dia. - Hei, ponselmu bunyi terus dari tadi.
I'm taking a dump before washing the motorcycle.
Berak dulu baru cuci motor.
Weirdo.
Aneh.
[sighs]
[menghela napas]
[Boy] You're heading to Jakarta soon?
[Boy] Kau sudah mau berangkat ke Jakarta, ya?
You're about to become a singer.
Sebentar lagi kau sudah jadi penyanyi.
I can't wait.
Tidak sabar.
But why do you look so down?
Tapi kenapa muka kau lesu begitu?
Hey.
Hei.
Thinking about Ade?
Terpikir Ade, ya?
[somber music playing]
[musik sendu]
[Boy] I think that before you go to Jakarta,
[Boy] Menurutku, sebelum kau ke Jakarta,
you should meet her one more time.
kau temui dia sekali lagi.
Have a proper conversation.
Kau bicara baik-baik dengan dia.
[indistinct, happy chatter]
[dialog samar]
[Ode] She's getting married to Arya.
[Ode] Dia sudah mau menikah dengan Arya.
He proposed.
Mau kawin dia.
What should I say?
Mau bilang apa juga?
[Boy] Oh. Well, that means you should move on.
[Boy] Ya sudah. Berarti kau harus melanjutkan hidup.
No point in moping around.
Untuk apa kau galau begini?
Forget about someone else's wife.
Untuk apa kau pikirkan istri orang?
Let's go find some girls from here.
Mending kita cari cewek di sini.
Maybe we'll get lucky.
Siapa tahu ada yang mau sama kita.
Sorry.
Maaf.
Looks like you're still not over her.
Tapi sepertinya kau belum bisa melupakan dia, ya?
That means you can't give up yet.
Ya sudah, berarti kau harus berjuang sekali lagi.
If you want someone or something, there's always a way.
Kalau kita mau ada jalannya, pasti ada.
Maybe you can meet her family, talk to her mom,
Kau ketemu keluarga besarnya, kau ketemu ibunya.
or maybe you can go to her and kneel down
Mungkin kau bisa bertemu dia juga, kau berlututlah.
and tell her you're serious about her.
Bicara bahwa kau serius sama dia,
That you're her soulmate.
kaulah cinta sejatinya dia.
Do whatever it takes to convince her.
Pokoknya bagaimana caranya supaya kau bisa yakinkan dia.
[ustad] As written in Surah Al-Inshirah:
[Ustaz] Dalam surat Al-Insyirah sudah dikatakan,
"Indeed, with hardship comes ease."
"Maka, sesungguhnya, beserta kesulitan ada kemudahan."
[ustad continues preaching]
Diterangkan pula dalam surat Al-Hadid ayat 22.
Sorry, I left this behind at the tutoring center.
Maaf ya, soalnya tadi ketinggalan di tempat les.
Next time, check your things before leaving.
Makanya sebelum pergi, dicek dulu.
[Ode] Ma'am, I'm here
Jadi, begini, Bu. Aku datang ke sini untuk meluruskan beberapa hal saja.
Ade and I…
Aku dan Ade…
I mean, Komang,
Maksudku, Komang…
have been dating for quite a while,
Kami memang sudah pacaran cukup lama, Ibu,
and we have dreams
dan kami juga sudah punya mimpi-mimpi
that we're working towards together.
yang akan kami jalankan bersama ke depannya.
I completely understand your fears,
Aku mengerti sekali kekhawatiran Ibu seperti apa,
but please rest assured,
tapi Ibu tenang saja,
Komang will always be your daughter.
karena Komang akan tetap menjadi anak Ibu.
I'm not taking her away,
Aku tidak minta dia sepenuhnya.
I'm just asking for her hand in marriage…
Aku hanya meminta Komang sebagai istriku saja…
Raim.
Raim.
I've accepted Arya's proposal.
Ibu sudah terima lamaran Arya.
I don't resent you,
Ibu tidak benci sama Raim,
but there's no future for you and Komang.
tapi hubunganmu sama Komang itu tidak mungkin terjadi.
Some things are beyond our control,
Ada hal-hal yang tidak bisa dipaksakan di dunia.
and this is one of them.
Ini salah satunya.
Because it's not just my approval that you need,
Karena minta izinnya bukan hanya dengan Ibu,
but also that of the ancestors.
tapi juga dengan para leluhur.
I hope you understand.
Mohon kau juga ikut mengerti.
It's not that I don't want to hear you out,
Bukannya Ibu tidak biarkan kau selesai bicara dulu, Raim,
but this conversation won't lead anywhere.
tapi ini tidak akan ada ujungnya.
I…
Ibu…
have arranged Komang's wedding to Arya on September 1st.
akan nikahkan Komang dengan Arya tanggal 1 September.
[somber music playing]
[musik sendu]
You're welcome to attend.
Datanglah kalau bisa.
At least
Setidaknya,
I gave it a shot.
aku sudah mencoba untuk berjuang.
I can't lose you, Komang.
Meme tidak bisa kehilangan Komang.
I've already lost Kadek.
Kadek sudah pergi,
I can't lose anyone else.
Meme tidak bisa kehilangan lagi.
If you're going to be with Raim,
Kalau kau sama Raim, siapa yang mengurus Meme nanti kalau mati?
You're lucky to have married Dad, the man you loved.
Meme itu beruntung bisa nikah sama Bapak, orang yang Meme cintai.
I don't love Arya!
Aku tidak cinta sama Arya!
Komang.
Komang.
I'm doing this for your own good!
Meme lakukan ini karena Meme ingin yang terbaik untukmu, Mang!
Arya is a good man!
Arya itu baik!
I know, Mom!
Ya, aku tahu, Bu!
If that's your wish, what choice do I have?
Kalau itu apa yang Meme mau, aku bisa apa?
I've never had a say in anything!
Aku tidak pernah bisa apa-apa!
[door slams]
[pintu dibanting]
[heavy breathing]
[napas berat]
[sobbing]
[tersedu-sedu]
[thuds]
[gedebuk]
[Ode] I want to go to Jakarta
[Ode] Aku ingin ke Jakarta.
and start a music career there.
Ingin jadi musisi di sana.
If you dream big,
Kalau punya mimpi setinggi itu,
keep your spirit high, don't let it hang low like a clothesline.
nyalimu juga harus lebih tinggi dari itu, jangan cuma sependek tali jemuran.
[Ode] What about you?
[Ode] Kalau kau bagaimana?
Do you have a dream?
Punya mimpi, tidak?
[Komang] I've always dreamed of seeing dolphins.
[Komang] Mimpiku itu lihat lumba-lumba.
[Ode] Dolphins?
[Ode] Lumba-lumba?
[Komang] Yeah, dolphins.
[Komang] Lumba-lumba.
No other dreams?
Tidak ada mimpi lain?
Making my mom happy.
Bikin Ibu bahagia.
That's admirable.
Mulia itu.
Wow, it's amazing.
Wah, bagus.
This is great. What do you think?
Bagus ini. Bagaimana menurutmu?
Sounds good. What about you?
Sudah bagus menurutku. Menurutmu bagaimana?
It's enjoyable. The high notes fit well.
Sudah enak banget ini. Suara tingginya pas.
-[in English] Low profile! -Okay.
- Sederhana! - Oke.
-As Andra and The Backbone would say… -Nice!
- Kalau kata Andra and The Backbone… - Cakep!
Not a pantun!
Bukan pantun!
It's "Perfect".
Tapi "Sempurna".
[chuckles] Let's hear it again.
[terkekeh] Coba, lihat lagi, dong.
Hey.
Hei.
[indistinct chatter]
[dialog samar]
Hi, Jono, Joni.
Hai, Jono, Joni.
Are you hungry?
Lapar, ya?
[guitar playing on TV]
[gitar dimainkan di TV]
[Ode on TV] This song is called, "Komang."
[Ode dari TV] Lagu ini berjudul "Komang".
[Ode singing Komang]
♪ Dari kejauhan ♪
Even though he's busy now,
Walaupun dia sudah sibuk sekarang,
he still remembers to send us incense.
masih tidak pernah lupa, ya, mengirim kita dupa.
Huh?
Apa?
So…
Jadi…
[Ode keeps singing "Komang"]
♪ Sederhana, tertawamu sudah cukup ♪
[sobbing] Dear.
[tersedu-sedu] Nak.
If your heart says it's Raim…
Kalau menurut kata hatimu memang Raim,
I will give you my blessing.
Meme merestui.
You have my blessing.
Meme akan beri restu.
But you must be completely sure.
Tapi sungguh-sungguh ya.
[Ode] Peace be upon you!
[Ode] Asalamualaikum!
And upon you peace.
Wa'alaikumsalam warahmatullahi wabarakatuh.
[Boy] And upon you peace.
Alaikum salam.
You're more and more beautiful.
Mama makin cantik saja.
-You're lying. -I'm not.
- Bohong, ya? - Tidak.
Mom, he's a celebrity now. His song is very popular!
Sudah jadi artis dia, Ma. Lagunya meledak sekali!
[music playing on player]
[musik melalui pemutar]
Why are you here?
Kenapa kau di sini?
Isn't today your wedding day?
Kau hari ini menikah?
My wedding day with whom?
Menikah sama siapa?
You released your song?
Kau sudah rilis lagu?
Yeah.
Sudah.
On August 17th.
Tanggal 17 Agustus kemarin.
A national anthem?
Lagu kebangsaan?
What's it called?
Apa judulnya?
No, it's not.
Bukan.
It's something even more sacred.
Jauh lebih sakral daripada itu.
It's called… "Komang."
Judulnya… "Komang".
You poor thing! [laughs]
Hei, kasihan memang! [tertawa]
Did you think it was about you?
Pasti kau sudah yakin itu kau, 'kan?
[scoffs] "Komang" isn't about you.
[mencemooh] "Komang" itu bukan Komang kau.
"Komang" means the third child.
"Komang" itu artinya anak ketiga.
I wrote it in three cities,
Aku buat itu di tiga kota
with three producers.
dan diproduseri sama tiga orang.
Seems like lucky number three is still a thing.
Ternyata masih berlaku juga, ya, tiga-tiga itu.
Wait, you haven't answered my question.
Oh, ya, kau belum jawab pertanyaanku tadi.
You called off the wedding?
Kau tidak jadi menikah?
I only want to marry Laode,
Aku cuma mau menikah sama Laode,
the Buton noble.
bangsawan Buton.
You poor thing!
Hei! Kasihan!
It's not you.
Bukan kau, itu!
Oh my gosh! [chuckles]
Hei, kasihan memang aku ini! Aduh! [terkekeh]
You're not the only Laode out there.
Laode itu banyak.
"La" means men,
"La" itu artinya laki-laki,
and "Ode" means overdose.
"Ode" itu artinya overdosis.
Oh, right.
Oh, ya.
But do you really…
Tapi, benar, kau…
want to marry Laode?
mau menikah sama Laode?
Our Qiblas are the opposite.
Kiblatnya berlawanan.
I know that.
Ya, aku tahu.
[uplifting music playing]
[musik penuh semangat]
[chuckles]
[terkekeh]
[dolphin chirps]
[kicau lumba-lumba]
[gasps]
[terkesiap]
-[exclaiming] -[laughing]
- [tertawa] - [berseru]
[both] Dolphins!
[bersamaan] Lumba-lumba!
-[Ode] Hey, over here! -[exclaiming]
- Hei! Ke sini! - [menjerit]
-[Ode] Hey! -[Komang] Over here!
- [Ode] Hei! - [Komang] Sini!
[Komang] Dolphins!
Lumba-lumba!
[exclaiming excitedly]
[berseru penuh semangat]
[Ode] I've never seen a jellyfish like this before.
[Ode] Aku baru lihat ubur-ubur semacam ini.
Don't touch that! You're not old enough.
Jangan sentuh yang begitu. Kau ini masih kecil!
I won't use a jellyfish. I'll get stung.
Siapa yang mau pakai ubur-ubur? Nanti aku kesetrum.
[Kadek] Komang! What do you want to do?
[Kadek] Komang! Mau apa di sana?
["Komang" playing]
♪ Dari kejauhan ♪
No dolphins today?
Tidak ada lumba-lumba hari ini?
They don't show up this time of year.
Lumba-lumba belum bulannya.
Besides, with all this trash, no dolphins would come near.
Lagi pula, tidak ada lumba-lumba yang mau berenang di sekitar sampah ini.
Let's go. We're gonna be late.
Ayo, sudah terlambat ini.
Wait a second.
Hei, tunggu.
For you.
Untukmu.
Thanks.
Terima kasih.
I'm sending out an echolocation signal. Can you hear it?
Aku lagi kirim sinyal ekolokasi. Dengar, tidak?
[Ode] Are you a dolphin?
[Ode] Memangnya kau lumba-lumba?
[Komang] Can you hear it?
[Komang] Dengar, tidak?
[Ode] What?
[Ode] Apa itu?
[Komang] My way of saying I miss you.
[Komang] Ungkapan rindu.
[Ode chuckles]
[Ode terkekeh]
[Mom] Aren't you going to shower? I thought Raim was coming.
[ibu Komang] Terus kok belum mandi? Katanya Raim mau datang.
[Komang] He's not.
[Komang] Tidak jadi pergi.
Ode has things to do in Jakarta.
Ode masih ada urusan di Jakarta.
That doesn't sound like a relationship.
Kalau seperti itu, seperti bukan orang pacaran.
Do you want to break up?
Kau mau kita putus?
[Ode] Ade, do you believe
[Ode] Ade, kau percaya takdir
that fate brings people together for a reason?
bahwa setiap manusia itu dipertemukan untuk sebuah alasan?
I do.
Percaya.
Then you should believe
Ya sudah.
that you'll see dolphins one day
suatu hari nanti, kau bisa lihat lumba-lumba.
and I'll be by your side.
Dan aku yang akan temani kau.
Dolphins!
Lumba-lumba!
[laughing, exclaiming]
[tertawa, berseru]
Over here! Dolphins!
Sini! Sini, Lumba-Lumba!
[Ode exclaims] Dolphins are so cool!
[Ode berseru] Keren sekali lumba-lumba itu!
Look at that, it's jumping!
Coba kau lihat, dia lompat-lompat!
["Komang" continues playing]
♪ Dan apabila tak bersamamu ♪
-Ode. -Hmm?
- Ode. - Ya?
I believe we'll be like that one day.
Aku percaya nanti kita juga seperti itu.
God willing.
Insyaallah.
Ouch!
Aduh! Nanti rusak!
What dance is that?
Tari apa itu? Hei!
Kecak dance! From Bali!
Tari Kecak! Tari Kecak Bali!
Komang, not yet. That's for your husband.
Hei, jangan dulu. Itu buat suamimu, Mang.
Why not? I'm just giving it a taste.
Kenapa, Meme? Cuma coba sedikit saja lo.
You should wait, dear. Be patient.
Ya, nanti, tunggu dulu. Sabar, Nak.
Is everything here?
Sudah lengkap?
Who's really your child, me or Raim?
Sebenarnya, siapa yang anaknya Meme? Aku atau Raim?
It feels like you love Raim more.
Kok sepertinya Meme lebih sayang sama Raim?
You're jealous of your own husband?
Kau sama suami sendiri kok cemburu?
Yeah.
Tentu saja cemburu.
Is this everything?
- Sudah lengkap ini? - Selamat siang.
[exclaims] Wow. That's a lot!
[berseru] Mantap sekali ini!
Who cooked all this?
Siapa yang masak?
Oh, it turns out to be my love.
Oh, ternyata kekasihku sendiri.
I'm off to Friday prayer.
Ya sudah, aku pergi salat Jumat dulu, ya.
What about lunch?
Tidak mau makan dulu?
I'd love to, but I'll eat after I come back.
Aku mau sekali, Meme, cuma sepertinya nanti saja pas pulang jumatan.
If I eat now, whew,
Kalau aku makan sekarang,
I'd be so full, I'd feel drowsy during prayer.
pasti berlebihan makannya, malah mengantuk nanti pas salat.
Okay then.
Ya, sudah.
Bring this and hand it out to the people.
Kalau begitu, ini dibawa, nanti dibagi-bagi di sana, ya.
Okay, Mom.
Ya, Meme.
I'm sure they appreciate having this every Friday.
Mereka pasti senang sekali, setiap Jumat ada donaturnya.
It's not a big deal.
Tidak seberapa itu.
Thank you, Mom.
- Terima kasih, Meme. - Ya, sama-sama.
No goodbye kiss?
Tidak salam sama aku?
[chuckling]
- [terkekeh] - [kecupan]
Okay.
Oke.
-Peace upon you. -And upon you peace.
- Asalamualaikum. - Alaikum salam.
["Lesung Pipi" by Raim Laode playing]
["Lesung Pipi" oleh Raim Laode bermain]
Happy Eid Mubarak! Forgive me, body and soul.
Selamat Hari Raya Idulfitri, mohon maaf lahir dan batin.